CHAPTER 1

Scoping & Coping

In December of eighty one, I moved to Houston, Texas from Fayetteville, Arkansas. It was time to go to work. Professors of Civil Engineering taught the delicate balance that exists between preserving the environment and utilizing natural resources for specific purposes. But the greatest lessons of college were learned from friends that joined in the joyous exploration of life and love. So it was with some sadness that I left Fayetteville. It will always hold onto a special part of my memories.

It was May 24, 1982, when my parents arrived to accompany me to the hospital in Houston where I was to undergo the last of a series of diagnostic tests. Previous tests performed by a doctor near my residence in Clear Lake indicated that a gastrointestinal disease may be the cause of my recent pain. He referred me to a specialist he knew to make a diagnosis. Early signs of a gastrointestinal ailment had occurred in my childhood. No one suspected anything more than a nervous stomach.

I was anxious about the tests because the pain was increasing with every day. We were all worried as we drove north on Interstate 45 from my apartment in Clear Lake. I hid my fears and tried to downplay the upcoming tests; but mother was quick to point out that “You always need to have your family with you anytime you go under the knife.” The knife? Cora is a deeply caring and religious mother. The daughter of a Baptist minister who shows her emotions with a tendency to worry. The fact that she was the first woman to be a rural route mail carrier in Fort Smith, Arkansas is indicative of her pioneer spirit and abundant energy. She believes strongly in the old adage; if you are going to do something, do it right. There were few jobs she wouldn’t tackle in her younger years. One that keeps coming back to my memory was her desire to be a bull dozer operator. On this day, all of that motherly love and energy was directed toward the hospital and focused on her youngest of three sons. She was keyed.

My father, Bill was quiet on the way. Dealing with Houston traffic was consuming most of his attention; but you could tell he was concerned. Dad’s a self made man. He opted to leave a secure job with Standard Oil and move back to Arkansas from California, after the war to open up a gasoline filling station, on the hope of the future. He had leased the station and recently retired from house building because rising interest rates made house construction a risk not worth taking.

As we walked into one of the famed Houston hospitals, we were in awe of the medical complex where much of the world’s pioneer work in cancer treatment and heart surgery is conducted. I told the hospital admissions clerk that I was scheduled to be admitted.

After a few moments of record searching, she gave me a puzzled look and asked: “What is the nature of your illness?”

“I’m scheduled to have a series of tests run on my pancreas.”

“The only doctor we have by that name is a psychiatrist. Do you need his services?”

“I am crazy. It’s part of my personality. There is really nothing that can be done about it.” She was nice enough to locate the correct hospital.

Endoscopy and Meeting Doc

My parents had left to make the forty minute drive back to Clear Lake, by the time Doc entered the room. It was after ten; so, he was straight forward and efficient in his examination and explanation of the endoscopy that he would perform tomorrow. Doc is a fairly short, stocky man who sits and listens to your symptoms before explaining test results or upcoming procedures. All the nurses were fond of him. Likening him to a lovable, little teddy bear that you just want to hug.

I don’t remember much about the endoscopy, other than the horrible aerosol spray used to numb your throat. I was half asleep, still draggy from the Valium, when Doc arrived that night with the results. Mom was quick to introduce herself and Dad; wasting no time in asking about the findings. Doc described the procedure which entailed the use of a scope positioned on a fiber optic cable to aid the search for the openings of the pancreatic ducts.

“Billy has pancreas divisum. This is a condition he was born with. His pancreas is divided into two ducts. Each duct drains digestive enzymes into the duodenum. The smaller accessory duct has a stricture. Which we believe is the cause of his recurrent pancreatitis.” Mom nervously asked what this all meant. Doc’s deep brown eyes reached out to my parents when he told them that I needed exploratory surgery. “We need to see if drainage can be restored; and if necessary, remove the gall bladder. The bile from the gall bladder drains through the head of the pancreas. It is possible that this bile drain has been squeezed shut by the inflammation of the pancreas.”

With a nervous look of disbelief, Mom asked, “Can we take him to Ft. Smith for the surgery?”

Doc explained, “There is no time.”

Mom’s hand pressed against her forehead as she looked at Dad for answers that no one had. “We don’t know anyone here that can do this type of surgery.”

Her nervousness was growing by the second when Doc looked her in the eye and said, “I do. We have him scheduled for surgery at eight o’clock in the morning.”

As I laid in bed that night, the words, “there’s no time”, kept echoing in my consciousness. Ignorance of the upcoming pain and trauma allowed for sleep. In little more than a day, I entered a hospital, met a doctor I had never seen before; and was told by that doctor that I was scheduled for major surgery.

Surgical Trip

A nurse with shot in hand awakened me with cold alcohol and a swift sting of the needle. My body grew lax and pressed against the bed. A nurse said, “Rollover onto the stretcher Mr. Scherer.” Mom peered over the rail as I rolled it on over. The bed made a quick turn out of the room and hit the doorway, knocking me sideways.

The nurse said, “Are you alright Mr. Scherer?”

“Ah… yes .” The lights passing overhead were mesmerizing. I couldn’t help from recalling Howard Cosell delivering a television commercial warning about drunken driving creating highway hypnosis. He says, “That endless black ribbon where the centerline becomes mesmerizing, with tragic consequences.”

I rolled through a set of large green doors. As my stretcher rolled on, nurses passed, joked, and greeted each other as they began their daily work. It’s about that date last night. The end of night shift is in sight. The new patient on sixth floor makes me want to get out the door. I was wheeled into a room full of patients that looked as sedated as I felt. A nurse said, “we are going to start your IV now.” The folks were shown the waiting room and kindly told: “The doctor will talk with the family after surgery.”

Mom squeezed my hand and said, “Hang in there Billy.”

I gave her a smile and a thumbs up, as I was wheeled into the room. A nurse asked, “have you had your pre—op shot?”

“Yea.” I rolled my head back. My eyes locked onto the clock. It was seven forty five. It wouldn’t be long. Cutter’s arrival was announced by greetings from every nurse within his sight. He grasped my foot and asked if I was ready. It’s easier to say yes when you have not had abdominal surgery before. His white hair admittedly gave me confidence in his abilities. I would later learn that he studied at Mayo Clinic for seventeen years; learning the art of sewing soft tissue. The kind the pancreas is made of.

With IV in place, I rolled through another set of large green doors. As my stretcher rolled on, I peered through the windows of operating rooms until the nurse stopped and opened another set of doors. I was rolling into the room when I came to an abrupt halt at the edge of a hard surfaced table. With assistance I moved across the bed and came to rest on a cold slab. I was reminded of a veterinary table; and I was the dog.

Electrodes were being placed, as I looked up into a cluster of bright lights. The anesthesiologist said, “We are starting to put you asleep.” In an instant, a noise in my ears escalated from a slight reverberation to the sound of a train rhythmically pounding railroad tracks. My field of vision turned black.

CHAPTER 2

Under the Knife

I don’t recall much about the week I spent in a small room in the intensive care unit. The mind purges your memory, to free you from the painful impression left. During the surgery, I lost a gallbladder and had the pancreatic ducts opened after scar tissue was removed. The scar tissue had caused the pancreas to become hard and fibrotic; beginning the slow process of dying.

I was single at the time; so my parents and the few friends that I had met were my only visitors. I do remember the green look on one friend’s face when he saw all the tubes I had protruding from my body, a nasogastric tube (NG) from my nose, two tubes draining fluids from the body cavity, and a bile drain from my midsection. These drain to a collection jar that is hopefully cleaned daily.

My tolerance for Demerol was very low. I had only been administered Demerol twice in my life. It soon became the lifeline to normalcy. Severe pain is a state well beyond normal, under any sane scale. The medicine is given to reduce the stress and trauma. Without it, pain drives you into shock. Administration is a welcomed sight and feeling. I passed in and out of narcotic dreams during the week, with only one unusual occurrence, hiccoughs. When you have stitches extending from your breastbone to below the navel with numerous internal stitches, hiccoughs are serious. Arrival of each hiccough was broadcast in cries of pain. I watched as my nurse quickly prepared a special cocktail. Fourteen hours after a large dose of Thorazine, I woke up without the hiccoughs.

After one week, I was transported to a single room. Cutter felt that I needed complete rest, which doesn’t include roommates. As he wrote the orders, he rested the clipboard on my stomach. He must have felt that it was a good sign if the patient didn’t yelp. After arrival on the floor, an attractive doctor poked her head around the corner of the door and asked if she could talk to me for a moment. This woman could do whatever she felt like doing as far as I was concerned. She explained that she had observed my surgery along with a group of visitors because it was a rare procedure; being published only six months ago.

“I couldn’t understand what in the world could have happened to put a man as young as you into four and a half hours of surgery. I know now. It’s been rough so far hasn’t it.”

I answered with a yes, which led to a short but thoughtful few moments of conversation.

The Alcoholic

A patient next door had come to Houston from New Mexico to be treated by my doctors. A cyst on his pancreas had developed from his alcoholism; and surgery was required. Alcohol is a known toxin to the pancreas. He had been through it. He was wound so tight from coming off narcotics and being dry that he seemed to be appearing in a three dimensional movie when he would come in and give every one a pep talk about battling the evil that he and I shared. The Demerol may have had something to do with my perception.

The particular evil my mother was most interested in was his alcoholism. She asked her question by suggesting an answer to how much he drank each day, a pint. “Lady, I drank that much in the morning to get my hands to stop shaking so that I could make breakfast.” I imagined someone on a wagon train going west, killing pancreas pain with whiskey, only to have the pain increase with each gulp.

Pulling Tubes

Although not widely known, having drainage tubes removed from one’s midsection is the closest a man can come to the miracle of birth. Cutter is especially skilled at diverting your attention to keep you relaxed; so, the tubes can be out and in the trash can before you can complete your first scream. A quick hot flash is followed by a deep gasp for air.

Eating and Other Bodily Functions

Within ten days, I could walk with minimal pain and my diet was being advanced to full liquids. One of the ways of confirming that your intestines are functioning is the observance of passing gas. Each day, I had the privilege of discussing this occurrence with the nurses, Mom, Dad, and Doc. This greatly affects your humility. Once solid food was introduced into my diet, it was a challenge to eat even a portion of a meal. My intestines were sore from handling during surgery; having to be coaxed into functioning again. A hamburger felt like a twelve course meal.

Relapse

June 8, 1982; 13 days post surgery.

Up to now the recovery had been unremarkable; however on this day, pain returned along with nausea and vomiting. The pain is reported to be as intense as kidney stone passage or birth. Because I have not experienced either of these two bodily functions, I can only say it feels similar to what I imagine being shot with an arrow would feel like. Serum amylase, a pancreatic enzyme utilized to gauge the degree of severeness of the pancreatitis, was back up to three sixty five, from a low of one ninety seven on June 2nd. Demerol dosage was increased to the maximum allowable for my weight and combined with Phenergan for nausea control and to potentiate the pain killing effect.

Mom held my hand while telling me to stay calm and relax. I felt a sense of swelling under my breastbone; followed by piercing pain penetrating from the breastbone to the left of my spine. I grabbed for the call button and punched it as hard as I could, in hopes of the signal somehow getting there faster. It had been less than three hours since my last shot, a fact that Mom reminded me of. Relaxation was inconceivable. Instead, pain was met with grimace expressed from a fetal position. Muscles hardened with tension, as my face slid across the bed. Dad said, “Can’t they give him something for the pain?” I pushed the button again. Pain does not create patience. The syringe in the nurse’s hand brought hope. The shot was completed with pain of its own as the viscous Phenergan followed the Demerol in.

The nurse explained, “He can have it after two and a half hours, if I think he needs it.”

I had no doubt about the need. I waited in anticipation of the numbness, to be devoid of sensation, floating. My nose tingled and itched; my eyes began to glaze as I stared out the window at a bright blue sky. Euphoria took hold for a few moments. Closing my eyes, I drifted into sleep; further away from painful reality.

I awoke to the gentle shaking of my shoulder. Mom softly told me that supper was here. I could tell by the smell of it that eating was not going to be easy. The food began to create new pain. As I reached for the call button, I told Mom I couldn’t eat. My buttock was visibly swollen like football hip pads and spotted with green and blue circular bruises that marked where shots entered. Mother’s concern about my inactivity was answered by Doc telling Mom and Dad that I needed total bed rest. They went home early that night, knowing that a decision had to be made about the course of treatment; but, it wouldn’t be made tonight.

The next day I could hear Doc’s shoes shuffling my way. He always wore a smile, even when his day began early in the morning with an emergency, as it did on this day. After greeting my parents, Doc began to lay out his plans. “As an option, I would like for you to consider another operation.” The tail of the pancreas would be removed and covered with a tube made from a piece of intestine. This new drainage tube would be attached to the tail of the pancreas and the duodenum. With the ducts swollen shut, digestion of the pancreas would continue as would the chance for rupture.”

“Should we give him more time?” Mom asked.

Uncovering the whites of his eyes, Doc wrinkled his forehead as he calmly responded, “I have given him time. We will continue conservative treatment until three doctors I know have a chance to look him over.”

I answered his polite inquiry about my availability to meet with the doctors by stating that I could pretty much fit it in anytime between News at Noon and Gunsmoke. Everyone left the room that night feeling better than they did upon arrival, with the news that other opinions would be heard.

Confirmation

There was concern about rupturing of the pancreas. If it occurs, you die within fifteen minutes. The basic pancreatic fluid causes the electrolytes in your blood to precipitate. Loss of soluble electrolytes, required by the heart to keep beating causes an abrupt halt to life. Digestion of major organs also begins to occur.

One of the doctors asked to review my case was James “Red” Duke, a big character. His arrival was anticipated by all the nurses. He is a local celebrity known nationally for his ability to treat trauma patients. Doc studied with Red at the University of Texas. It was Duke who was a partner in inventing hyperalimentation, the IV fluid that I was receiving via a pump. A pump is needed to force the viscous fluid into an artery under my clavicle. It provides the body with all of the trace metals, minerals, fats, carbohydrates, and sugars needed to survive. Starvation was always a concern with pancreas patients, since patients couldn’t eat during pancreatitis episodes.

Wearing a cowboy hat and boots, Dr. Duke sat down and said, “Well Skeeter, you’ve got yourself into quite a fix here haven’t you.” I began to laugh as I whole heartedly agreed with his assessment. I offered to get up to allow him to examine me. “I’m not going to poke around on you. I’m sure Doc was thorough in his physical examination. I will look at your films and tests. God didn’t intend for us to operate on the pancreas; that’s why it’s located in such a difficult place and position to get to.”

In the end, each doctor recommended continuance of conservative treatment, no surgery.

Blues

My attention span was drastically reduced by the sickness and narcotics. Even focusing my eyes on television was difficult and reading was out of question. Hours were spent looking up at the ceiling, calculating the number of ceiling tiles and thinking about all of the combinations of tiles that could be assembled overhead.

Depression began to have a presence in my life. With stealth, you’re sought out when you become tired of the ride. A ride fueled by adrenaline. The low that follows is for now washed away by the Demerol. I began to lose my will to fight; opting for the needle more and more. I weighed one hundred and twenty five pounds at five foot, ten and one half inches tall. Nerves were shot. Drugs were used heavily. I began to receive the Demerol via the IV to preserve my rear and remove noise from the blood analytical work. Test results are altered by the damage of tissue that occurs when the syringe delivers the medicine into your body. Doc saw the symptoms of exhaustion and prescribed intravenous Valium.

My call button brings another reprieve. Quickly and passionately it deadens you, to float without worry, without pain. I was a junkie; sitting in a sterile room being fed nutrients from a bag. My eyes were encircled by shades of blue, green, and purple. One night, a nurse came in with a 100/25 Demerol/Phenergan shot, pulled my subclavian IV tube to her; and shot it all at once directly into my heart. Beads of sweat were all that I could express.

I couldn’t sleep one night; and I asked the nurse, “May I have a sleep shot?”

Doc had approved a sleeping medicine when I confessed to using Demerol to just get some sleep one night. A nurse responded, “I can’t give you a sleep shot.”

“Why?” I asked with some puzzlement.

She said, “It’s past three o’clock.

In response I said, “You mean I can’t have the sleeping medicine because I have stayed awake too long.”

“You need to ask for it earlier.”

The days past on until one day a lady appeared at the door. “Mr. Scherer? I’m with the accounting department and I need to inform you that your insurance company has informed us that they will not approve the difference in the cost for a private room as compared to a semi—private room.”

“Really!”

I opted to move immediately. I was able to get it approved since it was on Cutter’s order that I was sent to a private room.

Routines

There was one shining woman that performed the ultrasound examinations to determine if the pancreas head had shrunken since last week’s exam. She had blond hair; was trim. She always looked comfortable, at ease in performing her job. A few times my long stares that bread admiration if not lust would cause our eyes to connect. I had been in the hospital for a long time. All I could do was smile and ask how it looked this week.

“Better.” She quickly brought me down to reality by another squirt of cold jelly onto my abdomen.

One daily routine was that my electronic signal to the mother board outside the room would bring a personalized greeting by someone dressed to operate calling me sugar pie, honey bunch, darling, or sweetheart. To my delight, sometimes these greetings would be worked up into a little number to the groove of an Aretha Franklin song. What it takes to delight is obviously altered by continuous mainlining of narcotics.

Asking and receiving a shot is an experience in itself. First of all, you can be assured the nurse responding to your call will not have the keys to the narcotic drawer. Secondly, at least two other nurses will say they don’t have the keys and will make a wild ass guess as to who might have them. Thirdly, there is a chance that your nurse is working on another patient; so, you will have to wait until she finishes. Fourthly, when you complain about waiting for your nurse to give you a shot, someone will offer to get it sooner than later. Lastly never ever expect to get a shot during report at shift changes.

I was throwing up in a pail, when Doc arrived. “How much did he throw up?” Doc asked.

The nurse replied, “A lot.”

Doc went out of the room while I was getting my face washed by the nurse. Upon his return, Doc informed us of his desire to put the NG tube back in. It had been removed, once I was able to eat and keep down solid food. I was happy to stop eating, which was only causing pain. There was only one thing standing in the way, the NG tube. It was originally placed during surgery, which relieved me from the ordeal I was about to experience. The nurse instructed my parents to leave. Their eyes and mine focused on the three feet of tubing that she held in her hands. As badly as my parents felt for me, their feelings could not compare to how bad I felt. My palms started to sweat. What took place, could be easily adapted to serve as a sort of tribal torture to carry out when nobody felt like shrinking heads.

Doc held the tube and lubricated the end. As he began to place it in my nose, he said, “Here we go.” I kept swallowing until Doc said, “That’s it.”

CAT Scan

Hospitals have many ways to torture you in the name of science. One of the best around is the CAT scan, especially for pancreatitis patients because of the pain created by the four, twelve ounce glasses of lemonade you have to drink. This lemonade cocktail has a splash of iodine to top it off with that distinctive metallic, violently bitter blast of refreshment. The test can detect or rule out a cyst on the pancreas that could be the cause of the relapse. This is not a test that you volunteer for.

To make matters worse, this scientific marvel and radiological torture chamber is located in the catacombs, as I affectionately called them. The temperature is kept at a level that will cause at least fifty percent of the patients’ teeth to chatter and also keep the temperature at an optimal level for the operation of the machines. The proper gear includes sweat pants, thick socks, heavy robe, and blanket.

I was on my third iodine cocktail, when I answered the technicians inquiry as to my status with the news that I was starting to get nauseated. He disappeared behind the door, in search of a nurse. Perspiration beaded on my forehead. Saliva began to collect in my mouth. Hot flashes raced through my head. I urged a passing nurse to tell them “We need to do this now.” I was able to walk to the table, but needed assistance to step up and position myself.

Iodine introduced through my IV caused me to become flustered. I panicked and started to roll back and forth. I muttered, “I’m beginning to see stars.”

The nurse took charge and yelled, “He’s seeing stars. Let’s go.” She made final preparations. A cool rag was carefully wiped across my face as I stared into the nurse’s eyes. The nurse ask me to drink more dye to allow them to start taking pictures.

As I finished it, I asked for a bed pan. Not knowing whether I was going to throw up or have diarrhea. With my rear propped up by a pan and my head over a pail, I began the thirty minute process of inching through the CAT scan. The need for pan and pail subsided. Finally, the procedure was over.

Mom pushed me back to the room, to save me the wait for a transporter. With my head resting in my hand, I could hardly wait to get in bed and get a shot, to put me out of this exhaustive misery. With assistance from the nurse, I rolled onto the bed and rested motionless. Mom nodded with concern when the nurse asked if I needed a shot. She found confirmation from my facial expression of helplessness and a nod. I listened closely to each step. I heard the sound of the keys being handled and,

The keys making contact with the lock.

The tray being pulled open.

Latex gloves snapped on.

Ripping open the alcohol pad package.

Closure of the tray.

Footsteps to the room.

I see the nurse’s shadow on the door. Alcohol drips from the IV port. I begin to slow my breathing. I drift. There is sleep.

Getting on with It

No evidence of a cyst was found; however, the head of the pancreas was enlarged. Within a week the pain was reduced significantly. My spirits were up, despite the toll taken on my body. With this good report, clamping of the NG tube was initiated gradually. On June 24, twenty eight days after surgery, pain returned.

On June 28, another endoscopic procedure was performed. During the procedure, I woke up to see this black scope pressing into my throat. I saw Doc lunging to me saying, “Billy! Give him two more units.” The nurses held my head rigid and the scope in place until I passed out. After the procedure, Doc said, “I was afraid to give you more Valium, since I had already increased the dosage to overcome your tolerance.”

The pancreatic openings were swollen shut. No one was more frustrated than Doc. After all his effort and expert application of his training, the pancreas had acted abnormally. The strain of round the clock pain caused muscles to tighten, mind to become fatigued, and soul to lose hope. You awake at unknown hours of darkness to press the button that brings the quick relief and the return of sleep. The normal schedule of day and night is replaced by sleep after shots and hours of staring at walls. Sleep was my only escape. One I used often. Conversations with Mom and Dad after getting pain medicine were the most enjoyable times because it was the one act that even approached normalcy.

One day, I began to have pain whenever I swallowed. I didn’t make a big deal out of it; trying not to alarm Mom. After a while though, the pain began to get severe. Doc was at hand.

“I think you have esophagitis from the NG tube. It has rubbed a sore because it’s keeping the discharge end of the esophagus open.” Doc prescribed an antacid. I was so nauseated from the pain that I would gag when I tried to drink the antacid. Doc told the nurses to put it through my NG tubing. My bed was inclined by what felt like thirty degrees to keep the stomach acids from touching the ulcer on the esophagus.

Pancreas Pain Leaves

We watched fireworks from an empty room with a good view. There were plenty of empty rooms. No one volunteers for medical treatment on the fourth of July. Over the next two weeks, the pain level gradually reduced.

Oh, I still had some minor pain from the esophagitis; but it was nothing that could even begin to compare to the hell that I had been the center of. Although I was free from pancreatic pain, I still had an active NG tube. I wondered what difference it would make, when they began to clamp the tube. Food entering my stomach would cause my pancreas to produce digestive enzymes. The ducts would have to be open or pancreatitis would set in. On the twenty second, my bile drain was pulled. Now, the only tube left was the NG tube. It was time to start clamping.

Clamping was unremarkable; however, my temperature reached one hundred degrees Fahrenheit on July 28. Blood and urine cultures were negative. After the subclavian IV was removed, the fever broke spontaneously. On July 30, Doc stopped by and ordered the removal of the NG tube. Yes! I have been relieved. I was free to walk and leave my room. Upon removal, an IV was to be started on my arm. I am what they call in the business, a hard stick. I found this out when the night nurse came to start the IV. He gave it two tries. Another nurse gave it two more. An RN gave it another four and said, “I am not going to stick this man for the ninth time. Get someone from anesthesiology to place it.” I was so happy to see the anesthesiologist from surgery. She felt of the top of my forearm. I asked her, “Do you want me to turn the light on.”

“No. I go by feel. It’s in.”

It was time to eat. This is a process that takes a minimum of five days when you’re recovering from pancreatitis. First there is clear liquids. The staple of this diet is, as Doc so fondly described, delicious Jello. Then comes that old time hospital favorite, chicken soup, part of the full liquid diet. Given my esophagitis, soft bland was as far as I would get for a while.

Today was the day, when if all went well, the IV in my arm would be removed. I was talking to a friend on the phone, when Doc came into the room. I opened my eyes as wide as I could, striving to make two perfect circles around my irises. Doc was smiling from ear to ear as he saw me pointing to my IV and giving the umpire out-a-there sign. Mom informed him that I had been talking about nothing else since they arrived this morning. I finished the telephone conversation when he went to tell the nurse to pull it out. When he walked back in, I didn’t need to tell him how I felt.

Doc walked over to the bed. Put his right hand on my shoulder and with his eyes shining said, “I am so happy for you. It’s been a long haul.” Then he shook my left hand with both of his. Tears began to pond on my eyes. There was nothing else that needed to be said.

Detail

Mom had been washing my hair when it got so greasy that I couldn’t stand it anymore. I hadn’t had a shower in over sixty days. I have always taken hot showers. I let the water run over my head and neck, relaxing my muscles. This was the most pleasurable sensation I had felt in two months; unless you count the time I caught myself watching the hospital’s film on breast examination for women. I washed my hair three times. As I walked out of the shower, I lost my balance. I was far from physically fit.

The first few walks outside, around the hospital, were spent listening to conversations among visitors, nurses, and doctors about events that actually took place away from the hospital. There is another world. One day I was sitting underneath the front drive of the hospital talking to a world war two veteran. He fought in the battle of the bulge; serving under Patton for a while. When he was butt deep in snow, he made a vow, that if he survived the war he was going to live somewhere where it never snows. He said, “I’ve been in Houston ever since.”

Discharged

Tears were shed by all. I remember the car ride home with people talking on the side walk, car horns, trucks and the like. Once we cleared the city, Mom turned on a talk radio show. My view is that the hosts are rarely experts on anything. Being irritated by a radio show showed me how vulnerable I was emotionally.

On the first day out, I got a haircut. The girl washing my hair told me, “You have been taking a few too many drugs. I can tell by the stiffness of your hair.” To this I answered a resounding yes. I then explained they were legal drugs, much cleaner than you find on the street.

Jeff, my new roommate, had lived with my parents all summer. It was a lot to ask; however, their schedules fit, since he worked nights.

Pain free; August 10, 1982.

CHAPTER 3

Short Bouts

I did pretty well until November the twenty ninth of that same year, 1982. I had been sitting in the company’s van trying not to alarm anyone as we drove home from work. Getting pain medication quickly was my highest priority. The doctor that referred me to Doc gave me a script for Tylenol with codeine. I took one while waiting for my credit card to be processed. I was being beaten mercilessly and beginning to show it. I called Doc; he instructed me to come to the hospital emergency room.

The nurse had undoubtedly filled Doc in on the pain level because he slid around the corner as he ran to me. Squeezed tightly into a fetal position, I saw a blurry Doc through my tears. Doc was direct when he said, “Give him 100/25 Demerol/Phenergan.”

The nurse said, “He’s had oral codeine.”

With firmness, Doc said, “Give it to him. He needs it.” “It’s coming in waves, Doc.” The pain was so severe that the shot only made it tolerable, not dead. I said, “Here comes another one.” With each wave of pain, I winced and Doc listened with his stethoscope. He ordered the placement of an IV, NPO (no intake by mouth), and use of Demerol/Phenergan again.

Stay: 11/29/82 — 12/5/82

Diagnosis: pancreatitis.

A couple of weeks after I returned to work, I sought refuge in a toilet stall. I was doubled over leaning against the wall. The pain was too sharp and in the wrong place for pancreatitis. Someone walked in. I asked him to get a nurse from the company’s medical department. I loosened my belt and dropped my pants to my ankles. Within minutes a nurse arrived. She was accompanied by as many as eight of my co—workers. She kindly helped me into my pants and a wheel chair. I arrived by ambulance for another short stay in the hospital. When your intestines are handled during surgery, they lose some of their lubricity. A loop of intestine will twist tight to shut off the flow of fluids and gas.

Stay: 12/15/82 — 12/19/82

Diagnosis: partial bowel obstruction.

I lived relatively pain free for three years after this last stay. In September of 1984, I married. Life was good in many ways. Professionally, I was earning more and traveling enough for it to be enjoyed rather than dreaded. I also began taking MBA courses at the University of Houston. Marriage was good, with thoughts of children. On June 5, 1985 this serene life was interrupted, abruptly with force. Soon after admission, I began to hiccough. It didn’t stop while I was sleeping, eating, drinking, or walking for three days. Mom and Dad made the trip for this stay. Doc ordered: Electrolytes by IV, Demerol/Phenergan, progress foods as tolerated.

Stay: 6/5/85 — 6/16/85

Final Diagnosis: pancreatitis, hiccoughs, musculoskeletal back pain, elevated SGOT and LDH due to intramuscular pain medicine injections, gastroesophageal reflux.

It's Chronic

This was the worst news there was. It meant that the pancreas had digested itself to the point where scar tissue on nerves was causing as much pain as the actively digested areas. It means your not going to stop hurting until the pancreas is removed. Even after removal, scar tissue on nerves in the bed of the pancreas could continue to send pain signals to the brain. Chronic, this was a tough one.

Every time before, I left the hospital pain free. This time, I would feel no better my first night after discharge. Mom and Dad were on hand when Doc discussed the final diagnosis. “Billy is going to have to live with daily pain now.” I will provide him with Talwin that he can take every three hours for pain. I will also give him digestive enzymes to reduce the production of enzymes by the pancreas. This intern will reduce pain created from nerves that operate the pancreas to make digestive enzymes. These nerves are encased in scar tissue, which causes pain when the brain sends signals for them to produce digestive enzymes.

Dad said, “Can you give him a stronger pain medicine in case he has a bad attack?”

Doc replied, “I would rather not. If he can’t make it on the Talwin, I can prescribe stronger pain medicine on a limited basis.”

I said, “I don’t need to start taking stronger medicine on a routine basis. Not now.”

Stay: 7/9/85 — 8/10/85

Final Diagnosis: chronic pancreatitis.

Preparing for the Slab

Work had become more and more difficult. Spending nights in pain and working during the day was causing weight loss.

The pain had mostly just nagged until tonight. Muscles hardened as I squirmed. It’s time. Doc is called. I take a Talwin. Admission is not fun.

After taking down all of my information, the same information given to them six months earlier, I get my wheelchair ride to pain medicine. To relax and sleep without waking up in two hours because the Talwin has been metabolized. The nurses were pretty good at reading a patient’s pain level. Only the essentials were done before giving me the wanted sting of the needle. I began to breath without tight chest muscles. I drifted quietly into darkness, a pale, thin, emaciated young man of thirty, with one hundred and twenty eight pounds clinging to my five foot ten and a half inch frame.

After several weeks of pain with little easing, surgery began to be considered. Prior to surgery every test known to man had to be performed to eliminate all of the possible illnesses that could cause the kind of pain I was having. I was allowed to rest one day before the tests began. Tests really are awful to begin with; but when you have pancreatitis, they’re really bad. Everything put into your intestines triggers the pancreas to produce enzymes, which causes pain to increase.

Abdominal series x—ray
Abdominal ultrasound x—rays
CAT scan abdominal x—rays
Chest AP x-ray
Gastroscopy
Urine analysis
Blood analysis

In the end, surgery was chosen as the best action to take. Cutter kept it simple and to the point. “If the duct openings can be established again for drainage, then I will do so. If not, then I will remove the tail of the pancreas and hook it up to your intestine by a drainage tube made from intestinal tissue.

Surgery

I was the first one on the list at 7:30 a.m. I took a pain shot at 4:30; consequently, the pre-op shot was not given at 7:00. I felt that I could make it until I was put to sleep. I gave the folks the usual smile and thumbs up.

At 7:10, Cutter shook my foot and asked if I felt alright. “No. I’m having pain because the shot I had at 4:30 has worn off.”

He said, “We’ll get you right in.” I entered the room as he gave orders to the anesthesiologist to get me under. “He’s in pain. Prep him after he is put to sleep.”

A nurse leaned over me and said, “I’m going to put you to sleep. Relax; you will be asleep soon.” Nurses were shaving my chest for the placement of the monitors. I could hear that loud train coming. Jimi Hendrix. Bam!

I awoke to severe pain in my front midsection. An oxygen mask is smothering me. I can’t talk. I point to my stomach.

Doc asks, “Pain?”

I nod in agreement. Doc said, “We’re getting your pain medicine right now.”

I kept trying to pull the mask off. Doc tried his best to soothe as he said, “The surgery took four and a half hours. It took a hour and a half just to get through the scar tissue; so, the work could be done. You did great.”

Mom told me later that my wife burst into tears when she saw me writhing in pain on the stretcher in route to intensive care. I have no recollection of even seeing them.

Intensive Care

“Mr. Scherer, I’m your nurse. Do you know where you are?” Yes was indicated by nods. “Mr. Scherer you have already pushed the pain medicine button. You need to wait a few minutes.”

I firmly said “Get some tape. I want to tie it down.” Trying again to somehow gain control; I tried to listen to music. I ripped the headphones off as soon as I heard the first notes. After several hours of screaming and hyperventilating, I convinced the nurse to call Doc. Phenergan was ordered and administered. The shot immediately put me at ease.

I now sat back and waited with some small degree of patience for the first flicker of the ready sign on my very own Demerol pump. I was still in pain; but now my brain allowed for some pondering of the situation.

I hadn’t slept yet when Doc arrived the next morning. He and the nurse that I had been screaming at, came in the room. Pleading I said “I apologize for everything I remember doing and everything I don’t remember. Just thinking about the pain that I had that first twelve hours makes me cry.”

Doc smiled and said, “You don’t have to think about it anymore.”

I was still awake at the first shift change, twelve hours in ICU. That first bath feels good, as long as you keep providing more morphine. The worst thing about intensive care is a close contest between the coughing and breathing exercises and the elastic stockings you have to wear to prevent fluid accumulation in your legs from lack of exercise. Coughing when you have internal and external stitches is at the very least difficult and painful. The nursing aids who witness your breathing exercises are stern when it comes to compliance with the regime. They also enjoyed the usual back and forth about having to do the treatment. He said, “Mr. Scherer you don’t want to die from fluid in your lungs do you.”

I replied, “Is it worst than pancreas surgery?”

Demerol dreams are a part of daily life in ICU. One time I was flying a chair at jet fighter speed. There was a bubble to reduce wind effects on my face. The scene was the great walls of the Colorado River in the southwest. It was fun. Suddenly there was a problem with the engine. I had to ditch it; not an easy task. I came in too short and went through a forest piling up large pine trees with the front of the chair. Snow was flying high and blinding me. I suddenly came to a stop. I’m awake now.

I was a couple of pints low on blood after all the cutting. One day the nutrition specialist came in to see blood that had been sprayed across me and the bed. She said, “Tell me it is not as bad as it looks.”

I answered, “No. It happened when they were hooking me up to the blood supply.”

She asked, “But you’re okay otherwise?”

Roomates

I popped the Demerol button whenever the wheelchair hit a bump on the way to my new hospital room. I was in a single room for a while. There were a fair number of empty beds.

My first roommate, was an elderly gentleman. He worked as a mister fixit at a local university. He couldn’t wait to leave. When the nurse came to draw blood, he would say, “I’m not giving you any more blood. You guys are selling that stuff out the back of the hospital.” They got the blood samples. Vampires, as I jokingly called them, always do.

He described a trip that he and his wife made to Africa to see the big cats. At the outfitter’s store he walked up to a monkey in a cage. Quickly, the monkey reached through the cage and grabbed an ear with each hand and screamed as loud as he could. When his doctor came by to discharge him, he was laying underneath blankets fully dressed in his street clothes. He had hardly eaten any food at breakfast. His doctor asked, “Have you been eating all of your food?”

“Oh yea. Oh yes sir. I’m ready to go.”

“Well okay. Make an appointment for two weeks.”

It was around eleven at night when my new roommate entered the room. A large guy with short hair, dazed and medicated. He passed out at home; and hit his head on the coffee table. He was originally injured when hit with a pipe that knocked him off of a drilling platform in Alaska. There was no railing to keep him from falling about two stories off of the platform and onto ice: cracked skull, metal plate, major headache. He was getting the max of Demerol and Phenergan. He preferred to get it in the arm. “That’s the way we got ’em in Nam. I was tortured in the war.”

After giving him his pain medicine, his nurse left with a smile saying, “Well, I hope that helps. Let me know, if I can get anything else.”

After about an hour, he begins to yell for a nurse. “I need pain medicine.”

Standing at the door, she said, “I have given you all that you can have for another two hours.”

“You need to call my doctor. Get him up here and let him decide what’s needed.” The nurse replied, “We’re expecting to hear from your doctor. I’ll discuss it with him.”

He needed more; wow, substantial tolerance. He stayed awake for most of the night, except for cat naps right after being medicated. His folks showed up the next morning. Turns out, he’s going to buy them a house when he gets his legal settlement from his employer. His lawyer sent a large bird of paradise flower arrangement. With slurred speech, he looked and sounded like a drunk. He continued on with a continuous need for pain medicine. With a crack in his skull, I felt for him. His parents were present when his doctor walked into the room. After kindly introducing himself to his parents, his focus turned to the roommate.

The doctor said, “You are taking entirely too much pain medicine.”

The patient replied, “I need it.”

Which prompted the doctor to say, “You don’t need the amount you are taking.”

The patient responded, “Are you calling me a drug addict? Because if you are then, there’s the door. I have a crack in my skull that hurts.”

The doctor replied, “You’re playing games with me.”

The roommate answered rather forcefully, “I am not playing a game here.”

The doctor said, “I’ll tell your other doctor about my concerns.”

The roommate unloaded. “You need to be concerned about getting yourself out of this room.” After the doctor left, he said to his parents, “How dare him call me a drug addict.”

His dad said, “Well, son I think there is some truth to the idea that you are taking too much. Your mother and I feel that way.”

Within the hour, his other doctor walked in telling his parents to “Please keep your seats.” Looking directly at the patient, he said, “I hear you are not doing well.”

In response the patient said, “It is really bad. Besides that the other doctor thinks I’m a drug addict.”

“I think he is concerned for your health; but he doesn’t have a crack in his skull. Try to cut down if you can, but don’t be in pain. Use the medicine for a day or two until we can be sure you are not going to fall again. Try to get up and walk around as much as you can.” As his doctor was leaving he said to his parents, “It was nice meeting you.” When he took the doctor up on walking, he found it difficult to find his room when he returned. What a trip. I don’t know if he ever got his settlement. I do know he will be in pain for the rest of his life.

Another roommate had a split personality; or you could say two fronts. To single women he was gooey sweet, eyes fluttering, high pitched “How are youuuu.” To his soon to be divorced wife, he was “You bitch shut up while I tell you what’s what.” He hit on an attractive vampire. He didn’t fool her.

Odd Happenings

One day my head became rigidly fixed with my eyes pointed directly over my shoulder. My neck muscles were hard, with severe cramps. I said to myself, “I have to control my mind to get my head turned back. Got to get it back.”

The nurse that answered my mother’s desperate call, slid into the room. She fixed her eyes on mine; then vanished. A brief moment later the room was filled with Cutter, his nurse, and three nurses from the floor.

Cutter said, “He is having a reaction to one of his meds.” He and a nurse went to get medicine.

I just kept thinking, “I have to control my mind.” A nurse entered the room with a syringe. I didn’t ask what the medicine was. Whatever it was worked. I slept for several hours.

It was time to go to the catacombs of x-ray land again for that good old time favorite CAT scan. As the transporter pushed me down the hall, two folding doors flew open. A young girl, maybe nine or ten was laying on a stretcher. She had pins protruding through the skin of her leg along a line from knee to foot. Her mother tried to console her. How could anyone be anything other than terrified with the pain she was living with.

As soon as I made eye contact with the girl, she was rushed to another room. That night Doc reported the CAT scan results. “It’s still swollen. We will take another look next week.” In those few words, Doc extended the stay one more week. I’ll get to enjoy those metallic iodine cocktails next week, and the week after …. and ….. after.

My subclavian IV had been in for a long time. It was removed to eliminate a possible source of infection. When they put the new one in, a group of nurse trainees hovered around my bed to watch the procedure. One of them said, “I bet you never had so many good looking women hovering over you in bed before have you?”

I said, “Well, yes I have.”

My mother enjoyed telling that story.

Discharged

April 15, 1986.

Finally after fifty three days, I walked out a free man. I had been in the hospital for the entire NCAA basketball tournament.

Admitting Diagnosis: Pancreatitis.

Final Diagnosis:

Chronic pancreatitis
Pancreas divisum
Stricture of minor ampulla of Vater
Stricture of common bile duct
Stricture of pancreatic duct
Esophagitis
Gastritis
Duodenitis

Operations Performed:

Endoscopic retrograde pancreatography on 3/7/86.
Exploratory laparotomy with lysis of adhesions, resection of the tail of pancreas.
Pancreaticojejunostomy and jejunostomy (Roux—En—Y), and choledochojejunostomy, and jejunojejunostomy (Roux—En—Y) on 3/11/86.

Wow!

CHAPTER 4

Sub-total Pancreatectomy

Because the pancreatitis had turned into chronic pancreatitis, hospitalization was required to observe the pancreas to asses the risk of rupture. The chronic digestion of the pancreas by digestion enzymes being produced and not exiting the pancreas due to closed ducts was causing a continuous risk of rupture. Because death would occur within fifteen minutes after rupture, this was a risk that had to be assessed.

From July to October of 1986, the pain would reach levels that had to be treated in a hospital. The severe pain was a sign of severe damage to the pancreas.

Stay: 7/28/86 — 8/4/86

Diagnosis: recurrent pancreatitis, diarrhea secondary to Motrin 400 mg qid.

Stay: 8/27/86 — 9/8/86

Diagnosis: chronic relapsing pancreatitis, chronic pain syndrome.

In August of 1986, I was transferred by ambulance to a pain management school at another hospital.

Pain Management

The purpose is to train your mind and body to relax in the hope of increasing endorphin production via self hypnosis. Endorphins bind to opiate receptors in the brain and produce like opiates some pharmacological effects including pain relief. At the very least, the relaxation techniques can reduce the physical strain of pain.

Being outside of the hospital for the first time in two weeks was fun. Classes started as soon as I got there. I was asked to join a discussion group. Everyone introduced themselves and described their pain. Reasons for being at the school included back injuries, drug dependence, and abuse of prescription medicines. The mix included a Houstonian house wife to the much less fortunate. You come here because everything that western medicine can offer was ineffective. These were desperate times being experienced by desperate people.

The treatment regime called for replacing narcotics with non-narcotic medicine, Motrin 600 mg qid, Carafate (ulcer protection) and Doxepin to reduce depression. I couldn’t help but notice that all the colors used to paint our area of the hospital were colors that trigger pleasant thoughts, mauve, light powder blue, small thin lines of yellow, and hints of orange.

For the most part this was a health spa, first class. It would be difficult not to be relaxed in this place. Your day begins with breakfast at seven thirty; followed by group discussion, biofeedback, whirlpool, massage, and acupuncture.

Self hypnosis is taught to initiate deep relaxation. First you learn to control your breathing. Calmly take a deep breath, then slowly exhale. Focus on a fixed object; then slowly close your eyes. Consciously begin relaxing every muscle. We all have a level of tension, that is effective in keeping us ready to act. With practice, you can calm yourself through this natural state of tension; and reach a state in between sleep and being awake. Use imagery to take yourself to another scene that disconnects you from the pain.

One of the doctors was called Pretty Boy by the women in the group. He was the one doctor that brought out the worst in me. He was arrogant and prescribed a lot of medicines. After completing the course, I returned to the hospital for observation; making sure I could live without narcotics. Although Doc was in charge of my treatment, Pretty Boy was managing my pain medication from a distance. On the second day after returning to the hospital, I had a severe bout of pain. I told the nurse to call Pretty Boy to order an appropriate pain medicine. She returned with a syringe. I asked her, “What is the Demerol dose?” Calmly she said, “This isn’t Demerol. It’s a nausea medicine.” Frustrated with a raised voice, I said, “That would be like taking a damn aspirin.” No other medicine came that night. For the common goal of something I have yet to establish, I stayed awake all night stressed out subjecting my body to repeated doses of adrenaline. Doc intervened with an order for Demerol/Phenergan by injection, which reduced the pain to a tolerable level. Doc asked me to start trying to make it by taking the Demerol by pill.

After two weeks, I was discharged with prescriptions for Mepergan Fortis (50 mg Demerol capsules), 600 mg Motrin qid, Doxepin, and Carafate to help prevent ulcers that can occur when taking large doses of an anti-inflammatory drug like Motrin. I was able to reduce the number and severity of tension headaches by using the methods taught at the school.

Back to Home Base

On December 20 1986, I arrived home from a business trip to Norway. On Christmas Eve I had diarrhea and malaise. I got over all that; however, the pancreatic pain was in full force. I was taking Mepergan Fortis (50 mg Demerol). I put myself on a clear liquid diet to reduce pain from eating solid food. After a couple of weeks, I made the call, “Doc, the pancreas pain has returned. I have been taking the Mepergan Fortis you ordered; but I have reached my limit.” He said, “Do you think you can make it until tomorrow morning? I said, “yes I think so.” “Come to my office in the morning to let me look you over.”

After greeting Doc’s wife who managed his office, she said, “I told him you called to let us know you would like to see him around ten o’clock. He didn’t schedule any office visits; and he’s not performing any procedures. He’s at the hospital. Let me call him and let him know you’re here. Have a seat. Make yourself comfortable. He’ll be here soon.” When he arrived we discussed my symptoms. “Do you think we need to put you in?” I answered, “Unfortunately I do.” Doc said, “Before we do that, I want to perform an endoscopy to rule out an ulcer. We can do it tomorrow afternoon, if you can. I checked the hospital schedule; and there is an opening at two. After the procedure, he met me in the recovery room at the hospital. Doc said, “You didn’t break a record for size; but, I found a 1.2 cm sharply demarcated bleeding ulcer. I think that is the source of your pain. I’m going to admit you for treatment of the ulcer and pain management.

After what seemed like gallons of antacid to cure the ulcer, the final showdown with my pancreas began as I was admitted into the hospital on May 24, 1987. I wouldn’t leave until September 1. I got the usual treatment, at first: NPO, IV, and narcotic pain medications. In medical terms, I was a well developed, well nourished, young male with chronic relapsing pancreatitis.

June was coming to an end; but the pain was not responding to nothing by mouth (NPO), everything by tube. Doc and I agreed to allow experts in pain management attempt to reach a discharge status via replacement of narcotics by anti—inflammatory drugs, anti—depressants, and amino acid drugs.

On July 2, pain management was taken over by doctors from the pain management school that I attended. Pretty Boy was my doctor. He ordered an elixir with a relatively low dose of Demerol. This eliminated the quick relief provided by injection into muscle tissue with a syringe.  Injection by syringe is considered to be easier to result in addiction. Doc left instructions for me to have the nurse call him, if I felt like I needed a stronger dose of pain medicine than what was ordered by the pain management doctor. He said, “Try to make it on their order; but don’t suffer.” Of course getting a nurse to call is difficult. Doc told me that “It’s their duty to deny pain medicine and provide cold bed pans.”

After three days of using the elixir, I was beginning to think I wasn’t going to be able to make it without using a larger dose of narcotic. I was confronted by the need for the drug and the cold hard fact that life cannot exist in a hospital. If my night is like this day, it’s going to be a long one.

I asked the nurse to call Pretty Boy to tell him I can’t make it without an increase in the narcotic dosage.

The nurse replied, “Mr. Scherer your doctor has ordered the elixir that has a narcotic in it. I said, “Then, please call Doc and tell him I can’t make it on the elixir alone.”

She said in a firm voice, “Please try to relax and go back to sleep.”

“Sleep!” I had been awake all night.

I walked the halls trying to get my mind off of the pain. I felt that I could make it until nine o’clock am. At eight o’clock, I called Pretty Boy myself. His assistant answered the phone: “He’s not in.” I replied, “then contact him by beeper because I need him to approve a Demerol shot for acute pancreatitis.”

Thirty minutes later, there had been no response. I convinced a nurse to call. She did and was told that he will be making his call backs shortly after he arrives.

I asked, “When is that?”

His assistant said, “Around nine.”

At nine thirty, I said screw it. I got Doc’s office on the phone. Doc’s wife answered the phone.

I said, “Hi this is Billy Scherer.”

She said, “Oh hi. Aren’t you in the hospital?”

“Yea. Doc told me to ask the nurse to call if my pain meds aren’t holding me. They aren’t. I did. She wouldn’t.”

“Let me page him. He’ll be over to the hospital soon anyway.” I was laying in the bed looking up at the ceiling crying my eyes out. My breathing became filled with stutter and tears. My roommate’s family was sitting around his bed, with the drape open. His mother leaned over as she asked if I needed a nurse. Cutter’s nurse just happened to be on the floor. She walked to my bedside.

She said, “Are you in pain?”

“Oh, I’m in here bouncing off the walls because he didn’t leave anything for serious pain.”

She asked, “Who didn’t?”

“The pain management doctor.” Uncontrollable cries came out. Her calm hand carefully pressed against my head. Checking my temperature, slowly caressing my forehead, cheeks, and my shoulder. Her caring came from her heart through her eyes to me, great caring.

I could hear Doc jogging to my room. She had left to get a nurse to give me a shot, when Doc came in. Through my crying, I tried to form words. Doc put his hand on my shoulder and said, “You did the right thing.” He instructed me to move to various positions. The shot came quickly. I got the max. I needed it.

It was around eleven when Pretty Boy responded. I was surprised to hear Doc take the call at the nurses’ station. I could hear him saying, “I believe he is having legitimate pancreatic pain that requires narcotic medicines to keep him relaxed until we can help him.” After the phone call, Doc left. Later that day Pretty Boy showed up.

As he walks in, polite hellos are exchanged. “Your doctor tells me you think the pain medicine we’re giving you is insufficient to control your pain.”

In response I said, “It’s not controlling the pain.”

He said, “You should have had the nurse call me when you began to need relief.”

“We did. The nurse called and I called.”

“When?”

“First at eight; then again at eight thirty.”

“At ten thirty, I received a message stating that you wanted additional pain medicine. I called Doc to discuss it with him. I was very upset to learn that pain medicine had been administered. I thought there was an understanding with everyone that we would be in charge of pain medicine administration. I’ll be talking to your doctor after this visit with you. What were the symptoms that made you feel like you needed additional medicines?”

I gritted my teeth and said, “Look. In all probability, I’m going to have surgery. This is a last ditch effort to prevent major surgery that I have had twice before. You believe that it’s okay to leave a patient, sick with pancreatitis, in pain for six hours?”

He looked down at me and said, “We are trying to reduce your use of narcotic medication. Never the less, you are receiving almost as much medicine as you were getting prior to our taking over the pain medicine administration. I’ll speak with the other doctors to see if any changes should be made in your medicines. When combined with self hypnosis and biofeedback, you can eliminate the narcotics.”

With a stern look, I said, “You have got me on four or five medicines when all I need is a shot of Demerol.”

In a defensive manor he said, “But if you keep using Demerol, your tolerance will increase; you’ll need more Demerol. Your body will reduce production of endorphins because the opiate Demerol is taking the place of your body’s own defense mechanism. Depression will then be a danger to watch out for.”

In disbelief I said, “What? You think the stress put on me last night is in some way helping me.”

“You can’t live in the hospital.”

“Someone that does not think this state of affairs is not depressing should have their head examined.”

He said defensively, “You are very angry. Are you angry with me, personally?”

“Yes. I think leaving a pancreas patient to be attended by nurses, without orders to administer the medicines needed for severe pain is terrible.” He left shortly afterward. “God that man brings the worst out in me.”

As usual I was near the end of Doc’s schedule because he knows that I’m a night owl. When he walked in, Mom said, “Well, you missed the fireworks when Billy met with the pain doctor.”

Doc said, “He told me that Billy was very angry and verbally hostile to him. I said Billy? I’ve never heard him be hostile to anyone.”

Mom looked at Doc and said, “You can only push Billy so far.”

Doc told me that Pretty Boy was no longer employed at the Pain Management School. Prior to surgery steroids were tried as a desperate measure to avoid surgery. It was ineffective. Surgery was the only means of eliminating the risk of the pancreas rupturing. If drainage cannot be restored, then the pancreas will be removed. Doc ask me to attend some classes at the diabetic treatment center in the hospital.

During that last week, I sat in on afternoon classes. I vividly remember the nurse giving herself an injection of saline to demonstrate the best method for injecting insulin. I was less than enthusiastic about giving myself a shot every day, even if the needles were small. The doctors told me that if there is a good type of diabetes to have, you will have it. I would have it because I wouldn’t have the disease. I just won’t make insulin. Persons who have the disease have a package of genetic weaknesses. In addition, I would be able to use the insulin very efficiently.

There was one other side to the issue. Not only would I not make insulin, I wouldn’t make glucagon either. Glucagon is the body’s natural safety mechanism preventing low blood sugar in healthy persons. Since the brain gets one hundred percent of its energy from glucose, I was definitely concerned. Additionally, blood glucose levels would be altered by the liver’s reaction to pain. It retains glucose to assist in fighting pain. High levels of pain cause blood glucose levels to increase.

Temporary or permanent nerve blocks were considered in consultation with another hospital. In the end, I was ready to take action and get on with it. The plan was simple. First, determine if I would benefit from filleting the pancreas down the middle and covering the organ with tissue; it would drain into the intestines via the connection that was put in during the second surgery. If the pancreas is dead, it will be removed. A small piece of pancreas, the rim, will be left because there are large blood vessels running through it. Severing of one of these blood vessels during surgery would create a life threatening situation. Additionally the pancreas produces hormones with unknown purposes and destination. Therefore the rim would be left to maintain production of these hormones. A portion of the ganglion associated with the pancreas will be removed. This area will be covered by tissue to hopefully reduce post surgical neuralgia.

There was just one hitch. There is a small percentage of people, who have their pancreas removed, who don’t achieve any reduction in pain. It was a chance that I was ready to take. Unlike the first surgery, when I was protected by ignorance, I knew full well how much this was going to hurt.

I had taken a lot of Demerol during this stay, increasing my tolerance to narcotic pain medicines. Even though it would be used, it was still going to hurt more than can be imagined.

On July 17, 1987, I could hear that loud train coming on the long black track. The pounding of the tracks came closer and closer together; then, there was the familiar lights out, bam!

Recovery

Doc was at the end of my stretcher, when I began to wake up. “We had to take your pancreas out. You did great.”

As always, my first words were directed at getting pain medication in the IV. Doc assured me, “They’re fixing it right now.”

I still had the oxygen mask on; I wasn’t trying to rip it off, like last time. My breathing was steady. It was a surprise to be able to accept the level of pain. Don’t get me wrong. It hurt, a lot. I pointed to my stomach.

Doc replied, “You want to know about the operation?”

I nodded yes.

“Your pancreas was dead. The pain you were experiencing was from the scar tissue pressing against the primary nerves that run from one end of your pancreas to the other.”

I asked, “What about the diabetes?”

“We’re going to monitor that closely. All you need to think about is getting rest. You look a lot better than you did during the last recovery.”

I smiled as I nodded in agreement. “I want the mask off.”

Doc reached toward me when he said, “Okay, here let me get it.”

I asked, “Was there a lot of scar tissue?”

He said, “Yes. He had to work for more than a hour to get through the scar tissue; before he could even begin to operate on the pancreas. Like I told you earlier, I’m going to be out of town for a few days. Doctor Martin will be watching you. He is very thorough. You are in good hands.”

I shook his hand. He embraced my arm and smiled with those warm, caring big brown eyes.

ICU

The trauma was significantly less since no intestines were cut. The biggest surprise was that my blood sugar levels reached above two hundred (Normal: 80 — 180) only once during that twenty two hour stretch before I finally fell asleep for the first time. I got a little over a hour of sleep. Subsequent monitoring showed no diabetes. The one thing that my pancreas could do was make insulin. It continued to make sufficient insulin with just the pancreatic rim left in my body. The rim was covered with islet cells, a condition called hyperplasia of the islet cells in the pancreas.

Although the pain wasn’t as intense, it was maintained over longer bouts. I was using a lot of Demerol. I had severe tension headaches that could not be relieved via hypnosis. Fioricet did the trick.

Back on the Floor

On the way up to my room, I winced every time the wheelchair hit a bump. After getting settled in, I put a wet rag over my eyes. I kept one hand on the Demerol button and one hand on the nurse call button. A middle aged nurse checked out all of the gauges and pumps used in hyperalimentation.

“I will be checking on you quite a bit tonight.”

My roommate had a swollen foot; something very common among diabetics. It looked terrible. A drape closed off my side of the room. I could hear the old fellow getting out of bed. He appeared at the end of my bed and began to say, “We’ve got to close this place up. They’re gonna come get us. I’m gonna close these window shades so they can’t see what we’re doing.” I hit both buttons.

The nurse gently led him back to bed. He limped back over as soon as she left the room. I hit the nurse button. Once again she pulled him away from the windows next to my bed. He was continuing his paranoia about invaders. We were on the fourth floor. When you’re doing Demerol and awaken, you don’t know if you’ve slept two minutes or two hours. I awoke to a surreal sight at the end of my bed.  My six foot tall roommate had a steel IV pole in his left hand.

His right hand was being put behind him by one nurse. Another nurse was injecting him with a syringe full of Thorazine. I hit the morphine button. Use of a straight jacket was discussed as they put him in a wheel chair. One of the nurses apologized saying, “He shouldn’t be in this hospital. We don’t care for mentally challenged patients.” The shot calmed him down, a lot. He was gone when I woke up.

Code Blue

“Code blue. Code blue. Fourth floor east wing. Code blue. Code blue. Fourth floor east wing. Code blue. Code blue. Fourth floor east wing.” The monotone voice from the intercom stopped. Standing in my doorway, I saw doctors running by the nurse’s station. I turned and looked into the room of a young pregnant woman. Three doctors were trying to save a life. Each action was announced and immediately taken. Following each procedure a doctor was verbally preparing for the next procedure if vital signs didn’t improve. The doctor’s were going through the calculated steps required to maintain life.

After about five minutes, her room was quiet. Doctors took turns washing up at the nurses’ station. It was my first time to witness a death, let alone two deaths at once. My chest felt heavy as I pondered.

The next week, I was awakened by a nurse, “Would you like to step out of your room for a few minutes?”

I was puzzled as I asked, “Why?”.

“Well, your roommate has died. You can stay if you feel that it wouldn’t be good for you to be getting out of bed. We could get a wheel chair if you would like one.”

“No. I’ll leave.”

This old fellow had been wailing in pain for five days; refusing to take Demerol most of the time. He had all the symptoms of pancreatitis. I guessed that his poor health and age precluded surgery. I shared my concern over lack of treatment with Doc one night. Being the professional he is; he just shook his head.

His son was crying as he left the room. He said, “I heard you talking to your doctor about my father. He had pancreatic cancer that was diagnosed during surgery.

Stunned, speechless, and feeling like a naive fool, I went out to the lobby. You can’t help but think about death in a place like this, especially when your roommate dies, a slap in the face to let me know that it could be worse. Death is the ultimate price paid for rest.

Addiction

This was without a doubt one of the strangest experiences of my hospital stays. Doc was on vacation for a week; so, one of his associates covered for him. After looking at my records and speaking with me he said, “You shouldn’t be having this much pain, this late in your recovery.”

It was a typical morning, when my parents walked in. I was on my knees pressing my head against the bedspread in the prayer stance. A nurse walked in and said, “I’m getting your pain medicine now.”

Mom responded, “Billy, you have got to get off of these shots; and, get out of here. It’s been almost a month since the surgery.”

“It hurts, okay.” During the day, we talked frequently about needing to get off the shots.

I was eating supper when Doc arrived. I greeted him by saying, “I think the only way I’m going to get out of here is to get off of these shots. I think I may be addicted.”

Doc said, “It would be very unusual for you not be addicted, given the amount of narcotic you have had to take to control your pain. But, you have been slowly reducing your use of the Demerol, which makes me believe that you’re near the end.”

I suggested that, “Maybe I should just go home and ride it out.”

Doc quickly stated, “No. There are serious reactions that can occur if one abruptly tries complete withdrawal.” He prescribed Mepergan Fortis in a capsule (50 mg Demerol) starting that night.

I slept for only a couple of hours. Frustration took hold, knowing that not more than twenty feet away was Demerol that would put me to rest. It was a rough night. For most of the next day, I took the pills as soon as time allowed. It was around ten p.m. when I heard Doc outside.

I pushed my call button. The nurse quickly responded. “Ask Doc if I can have a shot. I have been in pain for about twenty five hours.”

She looked at Doc and said, “He wants a shot.”

He replied, “What has he had today?”

“He has only taken oral pain medicine today.”

Doc didn’t hesitate to say: “Let him have it.”

Man, that sounded good. As Doc approached my bed he said, “The nurse told me you wanted a shot.”

I replied, “Yea. I need to get some sleep.” Doc said, “Try to use the pill next time. I will see you tomorrow.”

My parents left the room. I began to cry, when I hugged my wife. She consoled me. When I woke up the next day, I was pain free. I greeted Doc, “No pain.”

“Really,” Doc said.

“He hasn’t had any pain medicine all day. Isn’t that wonderful,” Mom proudly reported.

I would have sworn on a stack of bibles that I was having post operative pain. To get the drug, my brain was reproducing post operative pain because that’s how it got the drug in the first place. What a trip.

Stay: 5/24/87 — 9/1/87

Final Diagnosis:

Chronic relapsing pancreatitis
Chronic pain syndrome
Diabetes mellitus, post pancreatectomy, reflux esophagitis
Post operative ileus

CHAPTER 5

Breakdowns

Seeing Doc again was great. Doc inquired, “How has it been going since I saw you last?” “Good. I am the father of a healthy son.” Grinning with his big brown eyes shining, he asked “Pictures?”

Looking down I said, “I’m ashamed to say it, no pictures.”

“When was your last appointment?” Doc asked while thumbing through the file which was now well into Volume II.

I replied, “I believe it was October 1. I’ve been pretty much pain free since getting discharged. During the last few days, I have started to feel minor pain. It’s the first I’ve had since discharge.”

He inquired, “Does any one thing set it off?”

“No. It’s real shallow and not sustained. I’ve probably taken a total of five or six Talwin tablets (pain medicine). What could be causing it?”

He answered, “We left a piece of the pancreas called the rim in you. It’s possible that scar tissue is pressing against the nerves in that small piece. It could also be neuralgia; created by scar tissue irritating nerves in the bed of the pancreas.”

“What nerves?”

“When Cutter took out your pancreas, he cut nerves that once operated the pancreas. He also took out a portion of the ganglion in the bed of the pancreas. He covered the severed nerves with tissue; hoping to prevent regeneration of the nerves.”

“Why has it decided to get active now?”

Doc said calmly, “It takes about three months for scar tissue to form after abdominal surgery. It has been a little more than three months.” I asked, “Will it get worse?”

“I don’t know Bill.”

I was a little down about my future. Doc just looked at me and said, “Billy you’re alive.” I told him “I have a lot to be thankful for.” I just have to always have that at the front of my memories. Without the skill of my doctors, I wouldn’t be where I am today.

Two weeks after this appointment, I entered the hospital for eight days of Christmas hospitality. It was another partial small bowel obstruction caused by adhesions.

Diabetes

For several weeks in 1991, I had been eating a lot of ice cream and drinking fruit juice, unconsciously craving sugar. Without insulin, sugars are not absorbed by the cells for energy; blood glucose levels rise. Sugar Doc confirmed my suspicion by measuring my blood sugar. I was to be admitted into the hospital on Monday for schooling to learn about self treatment. Over the weekend, I remained inactive to prevent ketoacidosis, a condition that occurs when there is no insulin to turn food into energy. Instead fat is broken down starting a process that creates ketones. The result of this process is the conversion of body fluids into acids. This is an ICU event.

Physiology and behavior were taught to help diabetics learn to measure and inject insulin, monitor blood glucose levels, eat properly, and exercise, all for maintaining normal blood glucose levels from eighty to one eighty. It was a five day program. Mom and Dad made the trip. We were all concerned about the levels of pain that I was having. After meals the pain would escalate. It didn’t take Doc long to diagnose an ulcer. I asked, “Are you going to scope me?”

Doc answered, “We’ll take a look on Monday.” After the endoscopy, Doc showed me the ulcer on film. By the end of the week, I was feeling a lot better and schooled in treatment of diabetes. It is up to you to treat.

One of my roommates was a big fellow, probably two hundred and fifty pounds on a frame that was easily six foot tall. His dietician worked out his meal plans for the week, which accounted for the doctor’s order for him to lose weight. On Tuesday morning, he was sitting on the edge of the bed when the nurse placed his tray on the night stand. He uncovered the plate and just stared at the two little scoops of scrambled eggs, two small strips of bacon, an English muffin, and skim milk. He looked like a sad puppy dog looking down into an empty food bowl. “I’m gonna get hungry if I can’t eat sweet pies at work and have me a regular breakfast.”

Hospitalization

In the fall of 1993, Talwin failed to control the neuralgia. After six days of not eating much due to nausea, my stamina was severely depleted. Poor nutrition was taking a toll on my body.

I had called Doc to discuss treatment. I said, “Doc, I have been living on a liquid diet and pain pills since I spoke with you last week.”

Doc replied, “I think you need to come in to the hospital to let us determine what’s causing your pain. Do you want to be admitted as an emergency patient or go through general admissions?”

“No. Just go through general admissions.”

Nauseated from pain; and down to one hundred and thirty five pounds from one fifty eight two months before, I checked in for rest from reality. Doc was on the floor, which meant Demerol soon. It was especially quiet even for a Sunday. I was dizzy as I walked up to the nurses’ station with my shades still on.

Doc walked over and held my clammy hand. He said, “You don’t look good Bill. Nurse could you check his sugar? Doesn’t he look pale to you?”

The nurse responded, “It’s not his sugar. He’s at one thirty seven.”

Doc said, “Then he needs a shot. Give him 75/25 Demerol/Phenergan.”

Pain Management Revisited

After a week, I was transferred to the pain school to retrain and practice hypnosis and biofeedback. I would not be given any narcotics for pain. I began therapy by meeting the doctors, who sat around the perimeter of a long table.

“Are there twenty of you now?”

One of the doctors corrected the count: “Twenty two today.”

I said to myself, “expensive meeting.” A counselor I met during my previous attendance to the pain school smiled and waved. The group that I worked with during my original attendance had merged with a hospital to treat chronic pain, addiction, and other behavioral diseases.

One of the doctors asked, “Could you tell us your symptoms?”

“I had a really bad pain bout last week. I went to the hospital; and was given Demerol and Phenergan.”

“Do you feel that the use of the techniques being taught here can allow you to reduce and hopefully eliminate your use of narcotic medications?”

I replied, “Since my discharge from the hospital, I haven’t had hardly any pain. The Demerol I took at the hospital was effective in breaking the pain cycle, at least for now. The test will be when I begin to have pain again.”

Head Doc is one of those guys that hides his baldness by combing his hair from one side over his plainly visible bald head to the other ear. A psychiatrist, that is going to guide me through the rough and jagged edges of intense uninterrupted pain; and he can’t even deal with going bald. After entering his office, he closed the door behind me. He was my psychiatrist during the original training session in 1986.

I rubbed my hands together and said, “Look. I could bullshit you and you bullshit back; but that’s not going to do either one of us any good. I don’t think discontinuing use of narcotic pain medications is possible. There is no way my body can produce sufficient endorphins to relieve this pain.”

He said, “But isn’t that a self fulfilling prophecy? If you tell yourself you can’t do it, you will never achieve the potential good that can be attained by using hypnosis and the other techniques that we teach here. The quality of your life is being damaged by your daily use of narcotics. You’re isolating yourself from your wife, who is considering divorce. Getting off of the narcotics would help your marriage. About ninety one percent of people who have chronic pain get divorced.” As he said that, I slumped down into the chair in despair.

The stay was progressing normally, until the late afternoon of the fourth day. Pain returned after dinner. Dry heaves started at around three a.m. At seven a.m. I asked a nurse to call a doctor. A gastroenterologist showed up to work through my case with me. He said, “You are such a young man to have to have lived through as much as you have. Are you married?”

“Yes. We’re trying; but it has been really difficult for her. She has had to put up with a lot living with me and the chronic pain. I’m not sure we are going to make it. We are meeting with our marriage counselor and a counselor from your group today. It is very difficult to live with a chronic pain patient. When you say ‘I don’t feel like doing that.’ She believes it is because I don’t love her anymore. I still love her; but I may just be literally too sick to do whatever it is that she wants to do. That can be sex, going out with friends, or just going out together to eat dinner or see a movie.”

As he left the room I asked, “Can you give me anything for pain?” A wave and a smile answered my call as he left the room. I was ready for a shot of anything, any way. Finally a nurse with a shot came into my room. I asked her, “What is the medicine your using?”

She said, “The doctor has ordered Stadol.”

“Stadol makes my heart race. I’ve had it before; and my heart raced.”

She responded by saying, “Let me see if I can get something else.”

I said, “Oh, go ahead and give it to me. I’m so desperate at this point; I’ll take about anything.”

After the medicine was injected into my body, my heart rate jumped. Eventually my pulse lowered to a comfortable rate. Looking from the bed, my perpendicular view was imploded by spouse and counselors. I was strung out from being up all night mainlining adrenaline produced by my body in reaction to the pain. After the session, I informed them that I would not be attending my exit session with the Doc Troop, spouse, and counselor.

“You’re not going to go to your own exit session?” our marriage counselor asked.

I replied, “No. I am going to call Doc and transfer to a hospital where pain will be relieved by Demerol.” I called Doc and asked to be transferred. “Doc, I’m having acute pain again. I have been up all night with the dry heaves. There are no hard feelings over here. They just don’t treat acute pain. My pain might not be acute in medical terms; but it is very acute for me. This is a bout measured in days, compared to months and years.”

Doc said, “Okay. Well, let’s get you over here and we’ll scope you. Have you eaten anything since midnight last night?”

“No.”

Doc asked, “Can you get a ride over to the hospital?”

“Yea. My wife is going to take me.”

“After you are admitted, go to endoscopy and I will meet you there to help prep you.”

Admitting is never fun, especially when you are acutely sick. After being admitted, I went to endoscopy. Upon entering, I kept myself busy talking to the nurses. I knew most of them by name. One nurse asked, “What are you doing here?”

“I just missed you so much, I had to come back to see how everyone is doing. And, I like wearing these hospital gowns. They really set the trend in indecent casual wear.” Doc came in and said, “We can do it now.”

It was IV time. The nurse was having a hard time threading the needle into the vein. Doc walked up and said, “Let me try.” I offered a possible explanation for the difficulty in placing the IV. “I think my veins are constricted due to stress.”

As he missed the vein, he said, “I think you’re right.” He asked a nurse to go see if an anesthesiologist is available. He said, “They use these special needles. They won’t let anyone else use them.”

The nurse returned to say, “I couldn’t find either doctor.”

Doc finally got it stuck. “Can I have the medicine before you deaden my throat with that awful spray?”

“Sure. You want the pre-procedure medicine now?” I looked at Doc and said, “Yes please. I have been in pain all day.” Normally the medicine is given to you just before the start of the countdown. The technician moved me into the procedure room. I started to countdown from fifty to zero. Of course you never get near zero: 50,49,48,….At 30 I began going into dreamland. Attempts were made to awaken me. I didn’t respond; so the dose of Valium that is necessary to make sure you don’t wake up during the procedure was given.

After the procedure, I asked how it went.

Doc said, “You kept us all laughing.”

I replied, “Well, I don’t remember any of it.”

“You had a suture working through the intestinal wall. There was also mild gastritis which shows up on most of your studies.”

“It doesn’t sound like any of this would cause the level of pain that I’m having.”

Doc replied, “There was an area that appeared inflamed like an ulcer. I couldn’t get the scope into position to see it well enough to say for sure. Have you ever taken Talwin by injection?”

“No just the pills.” Doc wrote the orders that included a normal diet.

I was eating everything they brought in, with little pain when Head Doc came in to discuss my treatment. “Hi. How are you today?”

“Good.”

He followed up by asking, “What is Doc planning to do?”

Sitting up in the bed I said, “I don’t know. He saw a suture working into the duodenum and what appeared to be an irritated area that could be an ulcer. It was hidden behind a turn in the intestine. He couldn’t get a good view with the scope.”

“Okay, I’ll contact Doc about treatment.”

Doc came by as I was finishing off the last of my meal. With a quick step he said, “Hello. Hello. How’s it going today?”

“Alright.”

“It looks like you’re eating well. Don’t forget to eat that delicious hospital Jello.”

I said, “I feel pretty good. I haven’t had to take too many pain shots. I don’t know what the night will bring; but so far so good.”

Doc said, “I am planning on letting you go home on Monday if you do well tonight and tomorrow night.”

“Great. Head Doc came by. He said he would call you to discuss treatment.”

Doc nodded and said, “Okay. See you tomorrow.”

You could tell he had more patients to see. My plans for getting discharged were rudely squashed around ten o’clock that night. Talwin injections took care of most of the attack; but keeping my pulse rate from accelerating was hard to do. Thump, thump, thump pounding against my eardrums. Pain signals flew down nerves.

As the nurse gave me a pain shot, she said, “I’m going to call your doctor when my shifts ends at seven and tell him that your pain meds aren’t holding you.” I could hear her talking to Doc on the phone. “I am the nurse taking care of Billy Scherer. I wanted you to know that his pain meds aren’t holding him. It’s obvious that he is in pain. He hasn’t slept any during my shift.” There was a pause. “Okay, thank you.” She came back in to say, “Doc wants you to use Phenergan in combination with the Talwin until he can come see you. He thought it would be in a couple of hours.”

That, I could deal with. After lunch, Doc came in. I could only answer his polite inquiry to how I was doing with, “Oh I’ve been up all night in pain. I’ve been taking shots ever three to four hours. I threw up my lunch.”

With concern he said, “I heard that. The pain was severe?”

“Yea. So other than that, I’m feeling really great.” My words were broken up and washed with tears streaming down my face.

Doc asked calmly, “Do you want a pain shot?” Nodding yes, my hands went to my eyes and then to my robe to loose the tears. “I’m going to give you Demerol. Let me ask a nurse to bring it in.”

I could hear Doc speaking to the nurse “Could you give Billy Scherer a shot of 75/25 Demerol and Phenergan?” Returning to the room he said, “She will bring it as soon as she can. Don’t get too down Bill. I’m going to ask a neurosurgeon to come see you. He takes care of people in pain caused by cancer and other severe illnesses.”

I asked, “How do they treat cases like mine?”

“I don’t know. You can talk to Nerve Cutter, when he comes by.”

I inquired, “When will that be?”

He answered, “Hopefully tomorrow afternoon.”

Surgery?

Of what? Everything that could be cut is out. With a new hope, I anticipated his visit. We met and went through my history; something that I was getting good at.

He said, “Let me tell you about the procedure. The procedure goes like this. I’ll make two incisions in the middle part of your back. One on each side of your spine. The incisions are about four inches long.”

“The back?”

He responded, “Yes, until we reach the lungs.”

“The lungs?”

He said, “I’ll cut through a rib on each side of your spine. I can then reach the nerves, separate them from the lungs, cut them into, and cap them with a metal boot to prevent regeneration. It will help the abdominal pain, but you may not get much relief from irritated nerves in the pancreas bed. There’s not a lot that can be done about that. The nerves that will be cut transmit messages to and from the pancreas and brain. Since you don’t have a pancreas we can cut those nerves.”

I asked, “What are the side effects?”

Calmly he said, “The surgery can cause you to quickly empty your bowels. Some patients suffer from diarrhea. Since you take a lot of pain medicine, you probably won’t have that problem.”

I said, “I’m always on the other end of that one.”

He added, “When arising, you will need to sit up for twenty or thirty seconds before standing. Otherwise you could lose your balance. It could cause you to fall. I’ll call Doc to schedule the procedure next week. I’ll shoot for Friday. If you decide to have the operation, I want you to be admitted on Thursday to make sure you are ready for surgery.”

That night I talked to Doc about it. He said, “I believe Nerve Cutter can give you relief from a good portion of the abdominal pain.”

With hope I said, “I can live with the back pain. Not this though.”

I was sent home with a narcotic pain medicine patch and a narcotic elixir. Staying heavily drugged, I made it to admission on Thursday. After reaching the floor, Doc came by to tell me “The insurance company won’t approve an overnight stay prior to this operation.”

Bewildered I said, “The insurance company does understand the procedure?”

“Yes” he replied.

Angry at the insurance business I said, “Good grief. They’re going to slice to my lungs and they don’t feel I need to get ready for that?”

He shook his head and said, “I can only tell you what it says here in this note, taken by my office. They won’t approve the extra day prior to the operation.”

Frustrated I said, “Don’t worry about it. I’ll pay to be here. Insurance companies!” My blood wouldn’t clot fast enough; so, I was given a shot of vitamin K. Malnutrition from too many clear liquid diet days was the cause. The insurance covered the cost of the one night stay, since I received treatment that was required before the operation could be performed.

It was time. The familiar ceiling tiles passed like always as I was rolled to surgery. Call it experience; I could foresee the level of post operative pain. I knew it wasn’t going to be nearly as bad as pancreas surgery. As I was wheeled into the operating room, Nerve Cutter leaned over the edge of the stretcher and said, “I forgot to mention that this procedure can cause impotency.” The pre—op shot kicked in as I stared in disbelief. Afterward, I decided that I would have had the operation regardless of the side effects.

I carried on what I thought was a logical conversation with Doc in recovery. I was sent to intensive care for one night, an extra measure of care given my history and tolerance to narcotics. On November 15, 1993, twelve days after admission, I was discharged knowing what it feels like to be shot in the back with two arrows.

Once at home, I slowly started working to get my legs back in shape and gain strength. After a few days, the pain became increasingly worse and was hardly being controlled at all by the Talwin. I was about blow. I laid down on the bed to use self hypnosis to lower my heart rate and relax my muscles. I started repeating, “I can’t take it anymore…can’t take it anymore…can’t take it ... anymore.” Tears streamed down my face as I said, “Damn it stop.”

My wife did all she could to calm me down. She called Nerve Cutter to get additional pain medicine. She handed me the phone. I told him my symptoms.

He said, “You are having an anxiety attack. Give me a drug store phone number; and I’ll call in an order of Xanex.”

Anxiety attacks to me were something that crazy people had. I had to be at my son’s school for Thanksgiving lunch. I’ll get the pills after the lunch. The turkey and dressing had to be washed down with tea, a trick used when you’re nauseated but need to eat to prevent blood glucose from getting too low. My heart beat got louder and louder. I was weak. I made it to the bathroom wondering which orifice would serve to relieve. Afterward, I walked back to the lunchroom in a dizzy swagger. I was trying to force some food down, when my wife asked, “Billy, do you need to go home?”

I looked at her and said, “I may need to go to the emergency room.” Not wanting to alarm my son, I finished the lunch. Once in the car, she asked if I wanted to try the Xanex before going to the hospital. My hands were shaking. I began to cry uncontrollably. My arms and legs were going numb from hyperventilation. “No. Hospital.”

She wisely said, “Are you sure. Why don’t you try it first.”

Not thinking clearly I said, “No!”

She said, “Alright. That’s where we’re going. Okay? Relax. Do your breathing exercises to calm down.”

Tears were streaming onto my hands as I grasped my forehead. I entered the emergency room dazed and confused as I said, “I need pain medicine. I can’t handle the level of the pain I’m having.”

In disbelief the nurse said, “Who is your doctor?”

I answered, “Nerve Cutter and Doc.” I yelled, “I want to be admitted so that I can be put to rest.”

A doctor entered and asked why I needed pain medicine.

“I was discharged just the other day for an operation to severe my pancreas nerves. I’m having chronic pain and I can’t take it anymore.”

He asked, “Where is your pain coming from?”

I pulled my shirt away from the bandaged incisions. “It’s coming from this and the pain that caused me to have this operation.”

He looked puzzled and asked, “What did they do when they operated?”

I said, “They severed primary nerves that transmit information to and from the brain and pancreas. It was done to get me out of the hospital and eating without throwing up.”

He shook his head and said, “Rest a minute and let me talk to your doctor.” Another doctor entered to see what was up.

I was still crying, when a nurse told me “We are talking to your doctor on the phone.”

As she walked away, I cried, “Tell him I need to be admitted to get relief from post operative pain.”

She returned with the phone. Nerve Cutter said, “Mr. Scherer you are having an anxiety attack. Did you take the Xanex I prescribed?”

“No. I need to be put to rest; admitted into the hospital for a day or two.”

He answered, “I can’t do that. The hospital administrator would have my neck if I admitted you into the hospital, given that you were discharged just a few days ago.”

I said, “You’re saying that you can’t admit me for relief of pain?”

He firmly stated, “If you will go home and take the Xanex along with your pain medicines, you will get relief and feel better soon.”

In frustration I gave the phone to a nurse. I thought, “Hospitals are supposed to help people in need. I’m in pain.”

A nurse gave me a Xanex. As I walked out of the room to exit, the nurse that I had vented my emotions on said, “He’s approved a Demerol injection. Do you want it?”

“Sure, I would love it.”

My entire energy was directed at ending that pain. The shot hit with swiftness. I began to relax.

A nurse responded to my moan, “What’s that Mr. Scherer?”

I slumped down in the chair of the waiting room; and said, “I think chronic pain is a very misunderstood disease.”

One of the doctors said, “I know. If you go to treatment, you’re looked upon as an addict. At hospitals no one wants to admit on a chronic disorder.”

To me that was a nervous breakdown. Xanex was very beneficial during the next few months which included the guts of divorce.

Many Mini Visits

On one particular day, I began to have pain around my heart. Sugar Doc gave me a physical exam. An EKG showed no trouble with my heart. Sugar Doc said, “Lactic acid builds up in any muscle and causes cramps. You have been experiencing a rapid heart beat for a long time. You may feel pain there in the future. Don’t let it bother you.”

Valium replaced the Xanex. Blood loss from colitis caused Doc to perform a colonoscopy during my next stay from March 29 to April 5, 1994. The acute blood loss from my colon caused me to become anemic. Discharge papers read colitis, depression, diabetes mellitus—insulin dependent, hyperplastic colon polyp.

On July 17, pain initiates around my esophagus. The continuous stress from pain, causes my hand to shake as I grab a spoon. I can’t eat. Tears form slowly. Do you give up and go to the hospital or do you continue to battle? The tears get larger and increase in number as I rub my eyes and wail.

I make the call. “Doc, I can’t take it anymore.”

He asked, “Can’t take what?”

“Pain.”

“Do you need to come to the hospital? I ask you because you’ve had so much experience; you’re the one who needs to decide. Do you need pain management in the hospital?”

I said, “Yes. I’m a mental and physical wreck.”

“Come on in to admissions. I will write orders and send them over.”

After admission, a pain shot put me to rest. By the second day, the call for more pain medicine was extended to five or six hours. I catch myself laughing again, improvement.

The insurance company would only approve two nights in the hospital. Doc tried to get more but their doctor refused. After living with daily pain for months, you’re told to go home after two nights of rest. Your treatment is ended, not by Doc, but by the insurance company. Their doctor suggested that Doc send me home with a narcotic patch instead of hospitalization next time.

I was grateful for the time stayed. Demerol allowed for sleep of more than four hours at a time; breaking the pain cycle. The more you hurt, the more pain medicine you take. The more medicine you take; the more tolerant you become. This tolerance makes the medicine less effective; causing you to take more pain medicine. This puts you in a viscous cycle.

Stay: 7/17/94 — 7/19/94

Diagnosis: chronic pain syndrome, depression, diabetes mellitus—insulin dependent.

As a condition of my divorce, I tried to obtain ten year term life insurance. The insurance agent asked, “Do you take narcotics?”

I smiled and said, “Sure, every day.”

“You do understand this might prevent you from getting insurance.”

“In my case the drugs are prescribed by my doctor for chronic pain relief.”

In the end, the insurance companies would not bet on my life, not even for ten years.

My divorce was final on December 4, 1994. On December 6, I was admitted into the hospital for relief of intractable pain. Pain that worsened due to the combination of the constant stress of chronic pain and trying to work with little sleep and under the influence of pain medicine.

Diagnosis on 12/9/94: Diabetes mellitus — insulin dependent, esophagitis, gastritis, and neuralgia.

I filed for Disability benefits in May of 1995. On October 25, 1995, I received notice of denial of Disability benefits. On November 6, I cried for relief. Doc had become very frustrated trying to help me. As a gastroenterologist, there wasn’t much he could do except knock me out. I was admitted into the hospital on an emergency basis to get immediate relief by administering narcotics.

Before admission, we met at his office around five. “Doc, I am really worried about the near term and long term effects of living in this pain. I can’t keep doing this. I am living the life of a drug addict. I shoot up in the morning with the purest amphetamine, adrenaline. I come down off the speed with oral narcotics; and take Elavil to sleep. Pain and the body’s response, production of adrenaline, wakes me up in the middle of the night. I take more narcotics to get back asleep. My system is getting pounded everyday with stress hormones. To do this for another ten years is going to take a heavy toll. I’m afraid I’m going to start getting all sorts of stress related diseases after the age of fifty. Is there anyway that we can get the insurance company to pay for more than a couple of nights?”

He shook his head and said, “We can try.”

“Is there anything like frequent flyer miles once you’ve spent over a half million dollars at the hospital?”

“Ah, no.” Rubbing his forehead, he said, “I’m not helping you. I can give you relief with Demerol; but I’m not helping you reduce the pain.”

With face in hands and elbows on knees, I shook my head back and forth saying, “I need help. The other problem that I’m facing is a reconsideration of my Disability claim. They turned me down on the claim I made in May. My insurance company is going to drop me as soon as they can. It’s critical that I get Disability benefits because I can’t work. I stay up all night from the pain. I try to work under the influence of pain medicine. Doc asked, “What reason was given for denying your claim?”

“Oh, they said that my illness is not severe enough to prevent me from working.”

“Did you include depression as contributing to your not being able to work?”

“I filed due to chronic pain and depression.”

“Have you had suicidal thoughts?”

I said, “Doc they come in and go out, when I get really tired and worn down from fighting the pain. I don’t dwell on it.”

“But, you do have suicidal thoughts?”

“Yes. I have a lot of fight in me, Doc.”

“Let’s get you in the hospital and give you 75/25 Demerol/Phenergan through IV push. I will call a new doctor on our staff that has taken a particular interest in pain management. He is a neurologist. His name is Neuro Doc. He will be by to see you.”

Exhaling I said, “Alright. I need the rest.”

Doc asked, “How much weight have you lost?”

“Oh, I’ve lost nine or ten pounds.”

Doc put me at ease when he said, “I am going to admit you as an emergency admit. I’ll call in the orders for pain medication.”

I made my way through admissions on autopilot. When I entered my room, a man was wailing and oozing fluid from his throat. The pump on the breather kept a rhythmic pace; but his trachea tube had become dislodged. As I stepped back from the room’s door, his sister arrived to see him in the midst of confusion.

Looking to the nearest nurse, I said, “I think you need to see about the patient in this room.”

Nurses moved quickly once they became aware of this bizarre scene.

I had backed away from the room when a nurse leaned over the counter toward me and asked, “Would you like to move to another room?” I answered, “He’s in pretty bad shape. I think you need to put him in a single room. I’m nauseated; so I don’t really want to go back in there.”

I rubbed my forehead and thought, “just another day at the hospital”. The sound of the breathing machine alone would have been difficult to sleep with. Of course, the hospital is not a place to get sleep. Too many nurses make sure you’re awakened at least once every three or four hours for some type of care or monitoring.

After moving, a nurse walked in and said, “Hello, I’m here to place your IV.”

“I should warn you that I’m a hard stick.”

She stroked my arm looking for a vein. “Well, let’s see what we’ve got to work with here.”

It took a couple of stabs, but it was in. Now if only I could get a shot. It was night when Doc came by. “I see they put your IV in.”

I responded, “Yea. No medicine yet.”

Doc’s head snapped back when he said, “What! Give me a break.”

I said, “Get me one too while you’re at it.”

He spoke firmly to the nurse and said, “Dr. Scherer has not received his pain medicine.”

The nurse replied, “He hasn’t ask for it.”

With a look of disbelief Doc said, “He was admitted for abdominal pain.”

“We’ve been swamped with new admissions.”

As Doc sat down, he said, “She’s fixing it.” He began to go through the checklists that document the stay. “I know we’ve done this a million times; but it’s something I have to do.”

The nurse came in with the shot and pushed it fast. The Phenergan burned the blood vessel as it entered. “Man that hurts.” Looking at Doc with eyes bulging out, I said, “That was a little fast for an IV push. I can vouch for the nurse. When I came in, there were three new files for admits on the front desk. The nurse that gave me the shot was supposed to leave at the three p.m. shift change.” After Doc left, I closed my eyes and drifted into sleep.

I was hoping that the insurance company would give me at least three days. The next day Doc came by with good news.

Doc said, “I was able to get a week. I told the insurance case worker about your case.” She said, “That’s a really complex case. Take a week and call back if you need more time.”

With relief I said, “Great. I hope you got her name for the next time.”

Doc said, “I did. I told her that I have to explain this case to a different case worker every time I call.”

“Let’s hope we get her next time.”

“Neuro Doc will be coming by to see you this afternoon. I have to attend a meeting tonight; so, I won’t be back tonight.” He squeezed my ankle and said, “Take care Bill.”

Neuro Doc came by after lunch. I liked his demeanor and his positive presence. The No Pain button on his coat brought a smile as we shook hands. After a thorough physical, we discussed the major events in my disease history.

“We have been getting good results using high blood pressure medicines to reduce pain. We should try Catapres. It reduces the number of nerve signals sent to the brain. We use Talwin to intercept the signals that are generated. The pain is reduced by slowing generation and prevention of signal reception.”

He asked, “Do you use hypnosis and biofeedback?”

“Yes. I was trained in 1986 when the pancreatitis went chronic. I do pretty well, if I can get six to eight hours of sleep. What puts me into the hospital is when I begin to sleep in three to four hour sessions with no deep sleep. You do that for a week and a half; and you cry uncle.”

He shook my hand and said, “Hopefully the Catapres will help. I’ll continue the 75/25 Demerol/Phenergan for now. I’ll be checking on you in the morning to see how the night went.”

With gratefulness I said, “Thanks.”

After a couple of days, the boss of the insurance caseworker called. He was a doctor. Doc told him that both he and Neuro Doc recommended that I stay the rest of the week. He got the time.

On day six, Neuro Doc ordered to DC (discontinue) the Demerol. When he came by we discussed the strategy of having me spend the night in the hospital with only oral Talwin. I told him that “I think it is a poor use of a hospital stay. I can take Talwin at home. I can’t take Demerol at home.”

At two thousand dollars a day, I want relief. “Why don’t you let me get as much relief as possible while I’m in the hospital?”

With wisdom he said, “I need to know if you can go all night without the Demerol.”

As he walked out of the room he turned and said, “Can I talk with you about any benefit you received from the surgery done to sever the pancreas nerves that were on the back of the lungs?

I said, “Sure.” He sat down as I began to tell him what I had experienced after the procedure. I told him, “I did get a reduction in the nausea.” He said, “That’s good. Typically the reduction in nausea comes along with a drastic reduction in vomiting from the pain.”

“I benefited from the procedure. I haven’t vomited since I had the procedure.”

Stay: 11/6/95 — 11/13/95

Diagnosis: chronic pain syndrome, depression, diabetes mellitus — insulin dependent.

On the morning of Thursday March 11, 1996, I woke up at seven o’clock. I called Neuro Doc. “Have you ever had a patient that stayed up for like three or four days from chronic pain? I have been awake since Monday. I was doing pretty well until last night. I have just hit my limit.”

He said, “You must be getting pretty brittle. Do you want to go to the hospital where you last stayed?”

In response I said, “Yes primarily for Doc and Sugar Doc.”

“Go to the emergency room and I will write orders for you and call Doc. I will come by to see you; and talk with you about another procedure that we have achieved good results with.”

I asked, “Can you describe what is done?

He said, “The pancreas nerves collect above the rim of the pancreas in a nerve node. Because you no longer have a pancreas, we can consider killing the nerves at the node where they are brought together. They are only transmitting pain signals at the present time. As a first step we would inject novocaine into the nerve node; then we can monitor any reduction in pain obtained by the procedure. If your pain is significantly reduced, we can consider injecting alcohol into the node to kill the nerves and achieve a permanent reduction in your pain by eliminating the transmission of the nerve signals from the pancreas to the brain.”

It’s strange. The crying always happens after I have given in; realizing that I can’t live without extraordinary care.

As I walked toward the emergency entrance, a security guard quickly jumped to his feet and asked if he could help. I responded, “I am being admitted.”

I sat down in the admissions office to get processed. Cards and signatures to guard against liability. I rocked back in the chair and closed my eyes, squeezing tears to the sides of my face.

The clerk asked, “Why are you crying?”

“I have been awake since seven o’clock Monday morning in pain and I have reached my mental and physical limit.”

He said, “You are in pain?”

Talk about being lost in the ozone.

They were nice enough to give me a private room to wait for Doc. By the time I heard Doc coming, I had gotten most of the crying out of my system. “Hi, Bill. It looks like we need to take care of you again. Did you call Neuro Doc?”

“Yes, he told me to come here and be put in observation with pain relief to see if further hospitalization would be needed.”

“I see. Okay, well, let me call him and see what he wants to do.”

I could overhear the conversation, as Doc brought him up to date. “I think we should take a look too.” Doc’s shoes shuffle to me. “We are going to put you in observation. Neuro Doc will call in orders and be by later today. Okay?”

I began to cry when I said, “I only call when I’m crying and shaking.”

With a firm grasp of my arm and that big smile he said “We’re here for you.”

I smiled and said “I was doing pretty well until last night. I just crossed the line this morning.”

After the transfer to observation, I began the one hour routine. From the time that you get to the floor until you can even begin to be eligible for medicine is a little less than a hour of forms, exams, monitoring, and placement of the IV for pushing Demerol/Phenergan. My new head doctor showed up at about forty five minutes into the routine. He had been brought in to handle depression. Surprisingly he now shared an office with the psychiatrist that help me through my divorce. I liked him from the start. “What does Doc normally give you for pain?”

“75/25 Demerol/Phenergan.”

He wondered “Have you ever taken Thorazine?”

I told him the story of having the hiccoughs after pancreas surgery. “Well, I’ve been here for two hours and I haven’t had any pain medicine; so fire both barrels. If I get to sleep, I might sleep forever.”

“I noticed Doc had ordered only Talwin by mouth.”

I said “He’s not going to do anything about pain medicine.”

“Why?”

“He’s a gastroenterologist. I don’t have a pancreas. So, except for the colitis there’s not much for him to treat. He became frustrated because he wasn’t helping me by just relieving the pain. He wants you guys to handle the pain meds.”

He said “Let me see if Neuro Doc ordered anything.” He returned quickly. “I’m going to go ahead and give you some Demerol until Neuro Doc and I have a chance to talk.”

After the Demerol and dextrose disappeared in the IV tube, I laid back and closed my eyes to feel all of the narcotic .... peace ... and “Mr. Scherer, are you going to be able to eat lunch? It’s turkey and dressing.”

“Yea, I’ll try.” I got about halfway through it when I began to sweat. I’ll rely on the dextrose drip. It’s easier.

I awoke to Neuro Doc coming into the room. His face appeared distorted through eyes that changed the normal view to kaleidoscope. I rubbed my eyes for the first few minutes of discussion trying to clear up the picture.

“I understand that you have been given Demerol and Phenergan through your IV.”

I said yea 75/25, as my head bobbled back and forth.

He continued “Were you able to eat?”

“I ate about half of it. Then I started sweating; so, I quit.”

As he left the room, I fell into a daze. I could hear Doc discussing my treatment with my doctors. I couldn’t make sense of the conversation or anything else. Doc came into the room.

I asked “What do you think Doc?”

“I don’t like seeing you like this.”

“Oh, hey believe me. I don’t like being like this.”

“I think you have had so much pain for so long that you did like you said, you crossed the line. We’re going to move you to the diabetic floor sometime tonight. Get some rest Bill. I’ll see you tomorrow. Neuro Doc prescribed a continuous drip of Dilaudid overnight.”

“Thanks.” We shook hands.

The night before being discharged, my new head doctor came by and asked what my status was. “Neuro Doc DCed the Demerol; so there is no reason for me to be here.”

“Do you think he should not have DCed the Demerol?”

“I think I should get the most relief possible while I’m here. He wants to be sure that I can get by without the Demerol to avoid a possible re-admit. I understand that. I know that can cause problems for everyone.”

He ask “Do you want me to talk to Neuro Doc?”

I replied “No. I have voiced my concerns. I’ll just ride it out tonight just like I do at home.”

Stay: 3/14/96 — 3/19/96

Diagnosis: neuralgia, depression, diabetes mellitus-insulin dependent. Instructed to take two Talwin NX tablets every four hours for seven days.

I received a fully favorable ruling from SSI Disability on May 30, 1996. On September 11, my Disability claim was transferred to the payment center. Now it was only a matter of time to process and provide monetary benefits. I am grateful to have medical insurance.

On October 7, 1996, I was admitted into the hospital’s emergency room for chronic pain relief. Neuro Doc was to write orders for pain medicine; however, there were no orders for the emergency room doctors. After a hour and twenty minutes, I reach the floor with IV in place. Patiently I went through the routine of checking in.

When I asked for pain medicine, the nurse said, “We’ve ordered it from the pharmacy.”

“Ordered what?”

She said “Your pain medicine. He has ordered Dilaudid by IV pump.”

After a hour on the floor, the needle comes. The pump provided a slow drip of medicine while I slept. It brought me down with softness. Dilaudid provides a much deeper relaxation than Demerol; my outlook is pleasant. However, Demerol is the medicine used to control my pain during the fifteen months of hospitalization since 1982. It is that experience that gives you the mental fortitude to overcome the pain. Memory of all that pain allows you to see the current bout as one of many pain cycles that has been and will be broken. I must persevere.

In the afternoon, my sugar level got to forty five. I was sweating and shaking. Finally, I got enough orange juice in me to bring my blood glucose to a normal level.

Nurses removed the pain medicine pump around noon of the second day. That afternoon my sugar got too low. My nurse pleaded with me. “Mr. Scherer stay with me okay. Keep breathing steadily; try to relax.” Another nurse asked “What’s his sugar level?”

“I’ll have it in a few seconds. He’s at thirty five.”

“Let’s give him some more orange juice.”

“I think you are going to have to give me a D 50 (a viscous liquid containing a high concentration of dextrose)”

She responded quickly. “That’s why I’m trying to get the head nurse in here. I don’t have any orders for it.” Tears burst out and streamed in separate paths down my face.

The nurse said “Mr. Scherer why are you crying?”

I replied “I’m tired of hurting.”

She said “What’s wrong?”

I said “It’s accumulative; okay. I get severe depression when I’ve been in pain for a long time.”

Later in the day, another glucose meter reading indicated that my sugar level was low again. After another round of orange juice, I came out of it. I cried for a few more minutes after all the nurses left my room. After a hour or so, I asked for pain medicine. The nurse returned to say that only Talwin by mouth was ordered. I walked out to the nurse’s station saying “I take that at home for pain.”

My nurse said “We will give your doctor a call.”

“Thanks.”

Neuro Doc arrived shortly. “I understand you needed more pain medicine.”

In frustration I said “I’m angry. You can’t go from Dilaudid by pump to one Talwin every four hours.”

 He said “I called earlier and they said you were doing okay.”

“My sugar got to thirty five. I cried when that happened.”

He left to order Dilaudid. After about a hour, a nurse came in with two shots.

He was followed by Doc, who said “Go ahead and give him the shot.”

“We haven’t received his pain meds. These are for flushing his IV line.”

I said, “It’s been about an hour.”

The nurse said “Well, they want more time.”

In frustration, I laid back down on the bed. I told the nurse, “I’m not going to argue with you.”

Doc said, “How’s it going?”

“If my sugar had not dropped to thirty five and I had pain medicine, I would say we made progress. But today, I think we took two steps back. I went from Dilaudid by pump to one Talwin every four hours.”

Doc looked at me with a puzzled look “Are the nurses not responding?”

“There were no orders to respond to. They called Neuro Doc and he came by and ordered Dilaudid.”

Doc replied, “I saw where Sugar Doc had written orders.”

“I had them call him when my sugar level got too low.”

“Let me see if I can expedite the pain meds,” Doc said as he left the room. After a few minutes, he returned with my nurse who ask if I wanted the pain medicine. Doc said “I’m not going to be able to see you tonight, because of a meeting. Take care Bill.”

“Okay; thanks Doc.”

The orders called for taking a Talwin first. If relief is not achieved, I could get the Dilaudid. A solemn stare had the nurses answering their own question about trying the Talwin first.

Stay: 10/7/96 — 10/9/96

Diagnosis: depression, neuralgia, diabetes — insulin dependent.

Pain causes strange events. After I got home on one Friday night, I was really tired from fighting the pain. I fell asleep soundly around ten p.m. I woke up to darkness. I fully expected it to be light when I awoke. After my vision cleared, I went out to get the paper. It was Saturday night, eleven o’clock. I don’t remember urinating; but you would have to think that I did at some point.

Thanksgiving with my parents came with a trip to the emergency room at Saint Edwards Hospital in Fort Smith, Arkansas. After being up all night and feeling really jittery, I began to have severe pain at a level not experienced since my pancreas was removed.

Mom held my arm; supporting me as we walked to the Emergency Room. Entering the hospital sent a wave of tears flowing from my eyes. At the admission desk, a nurse gave me a tissue to catch my tears. I was quickly sent to a private room, where Mom held me while I cried. I said, “I just get so tired of fighting.”

With motherly love, Mom said, “Go ahead and cry.”

Always the optimist, Mom pointed out that we must be thankful for doctors and medicines that can help. After a few more tears, I got a 100/25 Demerol/Phenergan shot. I went home with Percocet and slept from one thirty p.m. to six a.m. the next day. I took a Percocet; and went back to sleep until noon.

I received my first benefit from Social Security on January 3, 1997.

After Dr. King’s Day in Houston, Texas, Doc got back with me on a call. “What’s going on?”

“I did this same thing on Thanksgiving. I need to go to the emergency room.”

Upon arriving at the emergency room, I was sent to have abdominal and chest x—rays as ordered by Doc. Afterward, I went to a room in the hospital.

I was squirming in pain as Doc came into the room. I had a wrenching gut. Doc held my hand and said “Calm down. Calm down.”

I said with tears on eyes, “I’m not exciting myself.”

“Calm down.” I stared at Doc, as he began to smile and reassure me with a grasp of my foot. I then smiled in return. “We’re getting your pain medicine right now. She’s fixing it Bill.”

A nurse said “Here you go baby. I need to draw blood samples. As soon as I knock that out, I can give you a shot.”

After returning from x—ray, Doc said “Chest and abdominal x—rays were normal.”

I said “We’ve got Thanksgiving two.”

“Tell me what’s going on Bill.”

“This is what happened in Arkansas.”

“What happened?” Doc asked. I drifted for a few seconds.

At six inches away from my nose, Doc’s big brown eyes looked right into my eyes. “Where is it hurting?”

“The usual spots, under my breast bone and all the way to the back.” I bared one side for the shot. The lights were lowered while I waited for a transporter. A couple of hours later, after moving to the floor, Neuro Doc arrived to see me stretched out on the end of the bed.

“What’s going on?”

The nurse responded, “Oh, he had projectile vomiting. He’s been one sick puppy.”

Neuro Doc laid on the Dilaudid by pump that provided a constant drip. My intestines were in spasm, severe enough to obstruct the flow. This caused the vomiting even though I had not eaten since morning. Because the pain continued, a CAT scan was done to look for kidney stones or cysts. I was on my final cocktail when an AIDS patient was wheeled into the room. His face hung on his bones. After a few minutes, I diagnosed him as manic. He was talking nonstop to everyone. “This is my fourth rectal surgery. I won the contest on the floor for the most operations. Will you shake my hand?”

I did and stared. He said “I had to spend some time in prison for molesting a nine year old boy. I just couldn’t stop myself. He was so gorgeous.” He was still rambling when I got the call for the scan to begin. The CAT scan was normal. One of three smear tests showed blood in feces. Colitis and the chronic pain combined to put me in the hospital for seven days. I was discharged Tuesday February 4, 1997.

After a few days, pain kept me up all night. With no sleep, I called Doc: “I need to get relief.”

With frustration he asked, “What do you mean relief Bill?”

“I have been awake for about thirty two hours and I can’t handle the level of pain.”

Doc said “You mean back in the hospital?”

“Either that or get Neuro Doc to give me some home remedy.”

Doc responded “Your insurance company is already reluctant to approve hospital stays. If we keep using the hospital, they are ..”

Finishing his sentence I said “Find some way to drop me?”

Doc answered “No. I think we need to be careful about our use of the hospital. Let me talk to Neuro Doc and I will call you back.”

“Hello Bill, this is Doc. Neuro Doc will be giving you a call very soon; so don’t leave your house. It won’t be very long. I ask him to work with you to try to make it at home.”

“Okay. The Houston Rockets are on TV. I can watch the game while preparing for lights out.”

Laughing he said, “Okay, take care Bill.”

“Hi, this is Neuro Doc. Doc tells me that you have insomnia and need pain control.”

“Yes. I’ve reached my breaking point, which wasn’t hard to do, given that I was hospitalized a few days ago.”

“Let me call in some Risperdal and a sleeping medicine. Give me your pharmacy number.”

He only gave me three sleep bombs. I slept eight hours on the first pill. Two additional nights of sleep were guaranteed. The Risperdal allowed for separation of the mental side from the actual physical pain. Separating the two is very difficult. If successful, you can realize that the pain isn’t any worse than it has been in previous times. The medicine helps you regain the mental strength necessary to overcome the bout of pain.

In Summary

Since moving to Denver, Colorado from Houston, Texas to live near my son in 2013, I have been taking 12 hour time release morphine sulfate (MS Contin); taking no more than two per day. In addition to morphine, I have also taken no more than one tablet at a time of Hydrocodone-Acetaminophen (NORCO) for breakthrough pain; not to exceed three tablets per day. Using NORCO in combination with morphine sulfate, I have been able to avoid going to the hospital emergency room for an injection of a strong pain medicine. Although an injection of a strong narcotic brings quick relief, it only lasts from four to six hours as compared to twelve hours from the oral extended release morphine sulfate. The hospital is not an option for me now. Every treatment, surgery and procedure available has been performed.

I have HMO Medicare advantage medical insurance. Once I was able to establish my network of doctors, it has served me well. I am very grateful to live in a country that has Disability with medical insurance. Not working with a Ph.D. in civil engineering has been difficult to accept; but it is a fact of life for me. A life that is lived not endured.

Current Medicines Related to Sub-total Pancreatectomy and Chronic Pain:

For Pain Management:

Morphine Sulfate 30 mg tablet ER 2 per day
Hydrocodone-Acetaminophen 7.5-325 3 per day as needed for breakthrough pain
Amitriptyline HCL 50 mg 3 tablets at bedtime
Venlafaxine HCL ER 75 mg capsules 2 per day

For Diabetes:

Tresiba Insulin 18 units per day
Humalog Insulin sliding scale

For Digestion:

CREON capsules 12000 units Lipase, 38000 Protease, 60000 Amylase 2 to 3 per meal or snack

EPILOUGE

New Memories

The events presented here were pieced together from the findings of a private investigator we hired to determine what actually happened. I have no memory of any of these events.

On July 20 of 2013, I was driving on Interstate 45 into downtown Houston. I took an exit off of the highway into a parking lot. A police car pulled up; followed by a fire truck.

I was laying on the ground next to my new truck which was on fire and full of gasoline. I was arrested for public intoxication. I am sure that I looked, talked, and walked like a drunk. After arresting me, we drove to the downtown police station. Before I was booked and jailed for pubic intoxication, a doctor looked me over. He said “This man is not drunk. He has head trauma. You need to get him to a hospital as soon as you can.”

Upon arrival at the hospital, I was helped out of the car; and onto a stretcher. Emergency room nurses took control. Answering a question of what happened, I yelled, “I fell off of a ladder.” I don’t think that ever happened. I was missing my medic alert tag and wallet. Nurses and doctors surrounded me and began to take control of the situation. I was taken to have X-rays and scans.”

I was admitted into the hospital on July 20. On August 10 I was moved from ICU to a semi private room. I don’t remember anything that occurred in ICU. While in ICU my lungs collapsed. On August 15, I had a Grand Maul seizure. This was followed by a series of small seizures on August 16. The next day I woke up to see my son and his mother (Mom). He lives in Denver, Colorado. She was living in Washington DC. I thought “This must be serious.”

They began to tell me what had happened. Mom said “The surgeon told us that my brain was being split down the middle due to pressure from blood pooling in my skull. You had a bleeding vein. There was concern that the blood may contact the cerebral cortex which would have damaged the nerves in the spine. The surgeon said that they were not sure if I would live more than three hours; so, he started a three hour operation.” I have a dent in my skull where the drill entered to relieve the pressure. The skull was opened by a procedure called a C-cut. I have scars in the shape of a C on each side of my skull.

With regard to what caused this episode, my guess is I got low in blood sugar causing me to lose my balance. I probably fell and struck my head on something.

My first nurse was great. He had been an army ranger. Upon discharge he studied nursing to work as a skilled nurse helping people in their time of need. My second nurse was not as effective. The doctors instructed the nurses to not let me stand by my bed without assistance because my balance had not been restored. Walking on my own was not allowed. The doctor said “Use a urinal. If you don’t have one, get one from a nurse; just don’t walk on your own to the bathroom.” This second nurse was sitting at his desk at the end of my bed when I asked for a urinal.

He didn’t respond. I said “If you don’t get a urinal, I am going to wet this bed. The doctors don’t want me to stand on my own.” I had a pair of clean flannel pajamas in the closet. Loudly I told him “This is your last chance to prevent having to change the sheets because I am going to urinate with or without a urinal.” After I had wet the bed, he walked over and said “You wet the bed. I will have to change your sheets now.” I said “Yes you will. Let me get out of your way.” After he finished changing the sheets, I put on my warm soft flannel pajamas.

I was sick from the chronic pain that was not being treated. Nausea from the chronic neuralgia pain and the condition I was in after the brain surgery was causing me to have trouble cleaning my plate. Mom said “Billy you are going to have to start eating what they bring you or they are not going to discharge you.” Without the medic alert tag to inform the doctors of my diabetes insulin dependent status, I was being fed fruit juices and protein drinks. My blood sugar was higher than the meter could register which was 600. The doctors were not taking my diabetes into account. The dietitian had not adjusted my meal plan to keep my blood sugar near normal levels. I overheard two doctors saying “We’re better than this. We should have detected this. Well, this will be easy to fix. It is just a matter of changing his diet.”

The man in the bed next to me was dying from liver failure caused by his alcoholism. He made it clear that he wasn’t going to change his ways. He had decided to go out on his own terms. The most unpleasant part of his trip out was his bowel movements made in bed. The army ranger nurse made it clear, while standing at the end of his bed. He said “They don’t pay me to clean up your mess. You need to take a little responsibility. Next time, get up and walk to the bathroom. If you don’t I’ll let you lay in it. Right now I am looking at a dead man.”

One day Doc’s son, who now was a doctor working at this hospital, came up behind me and shook my shoulders. He said “We are going to get you some morphine for the chronic pain.” I had met him when he was an intern working in the hospital that Doc worked in. He was able to get pain medicine for two days, which was a great relief. I got hungry again once the neuralgia was treated. I was eating when Mom sat down and gave me my medic alert tag. I asked, “Where was it?” She said “The police kept your wallet and medic alert tag. I was able to get them for you today. The hospital management office was very happy to find out that you have medical insurance.”

I asked my son what I was like in ICU. He said “Dad, you were talking to people who were not there. You also had hallucinations. The extremely high levels of sugar were giving you horrible headaches. You had a few seizures. One was a grand maul seizure. During the others you just stared into space for a few moments. I said “Well I don’t remember any of it.” It was August 21 when I was able to walk for the first time.

After thirty days, I was scheduled for discharge and transport to a rehabilitation hospital to learn walking and talking. At this point, I still walked and talked like a drunk. After thirty days, I was excited to leave the confines of a hospital. Checking into another hospital for another thirty days of care was dreaded. “Mr. Scherer the ambulance is here to take you.” the care taker said as he walked me to the door. I said “Wait a minute. I’m not sure I want to go. Maybe I could take a cab to my house.” In disbelief he said “Your wife and son think you need to go to rehabilitation.” I said “Maybe I could wait and think about it. Get a good night sleep; and, think it over.”

Later Mom told me, “I couldn’t believe you were not going to rehabilitation.” It was stupid of me, a good indicator that I needed to go. On my way to the rehab hospital, I thought to myself “Good grief Billy. You can’t walk a straight line and talk in a normal voice. You need help.”

The best part of rehab was my morning walk around the hospital. My physical therapist played defensive end for the University of Oklahoma football team. He was easy to talk to. Getting outside was such a joy. I was being treated with oral medicine for the neuralgia; that and being free to go outside any time I wanted was great. There was a flower garden with a bench seat. I had one bad bout of neuralgia pain that made me nauseated. I asked the nurse for some Phenergan. She said “We don’t provide that because some people used it to get high.”

The best food eaten was part of a group activity one day. We made smoothies and fruit pizza. Fruit pizza is a graham cracker crust filled with layers of fresh fruit. Needless to say all of the diabetics were followed to their rooms for blood sugar monitoring and insulin injection.

I left this rehabilitation hospital and moved to another hospital for another thirty days of rehabilitation. The patients would get together in the afternoon around tables to shoot the bull. One day I was explaining my experience of getting arrested and taken to the drunk tank. I explained that getting arrested turned out to be the best thing that could have happened to me because I got to a doctor faster than I could have otherwise. From the doctor’s evaluation, I was taken to the best trauma center in the region quickly. One of the old fellows across the table from me pointed to the sky and said “Somebody was looking out for you that day.” If the police had thrown me into the drunk tank, I could have past out for longer than the three hours the surgeon thought might be the time I had left to live. If that had occurred there would have been an article in the daily paper with a headline that read “Man put in drunk tank dies from head trauma.” If there had not been a doctor at the police station, I think I could have died that day.

Prior to the head trauma episode, I had planned on moving to Denver to live near my son. Seeing him on a few holidays a year wasn’t living life to it’s fullest. Until I could get a place of my own, I lived with him in his apartment. Because I had seizures after the brain surgery I was taking anti seizure medicine. Until we got the dosage correct, I was falling a lot. I would be just walking on pavement and my legs would buckle out from under me. I no longer fall on my own.

Another strange affect of the surgery was my lack of ability to control my speaking. I would start talking and wouldn’t stop no matter how long it went on. This was stressful on my relationship with my roommate, son.

After the head trauma and brain surgery, I developed memories of events that did not happen. Even when I was in ICU I was telling tall tales. I informed my son that while living in Clear Lake, Texas I met a man that was in charge of groundskeeping at my apartment complex who was once the King of New Orleans.

I asked my son “Did I tell you about going to Doc’s vacation home in the mountains near Denver? I went last May for a weekend. He was having a retirement party. There were eighteen or twenty people there.” He responded “Dad you didn’t come up here in May.” In response I said, “I don’t tell you about everything I do.”

I also told him that I had talked to Doc before the head trauma. After explaining that I couldn’t remember anything that had happened for the previous seven days, I asked him what could be the cause of the memory loss.” Doc said, “You sound like someone that is going to have a seizure. I will prepare the hospital for your possible arrival. You get an ambulance ready in case you need one.”

Before I left Houston, I dated a girl for a while. We were progressing in the relationship to the point where she was able to get me nude. We were standing in front of a large window. She touched the window and said “We’re not alone.” Later she said that “satellites see into my house.” She was in a four girl band that became nationally popular for singing Christian songs. There was a scandal when the news found out that she and the other band members were singing blues in bars. She was also doing a lot of drugs; living a wild life. The media found this out, which embarrassed her father who was on a speaking tour holding Christian concerts with her band. It was quite a coincidence that her father had approached Doc to speak at his meetings about the good work done by him and the medical community in Houston. Doc approached me to speak at one of their meetings when they asked him if he could bring along one of his patients to discuss the help that Doc had provided. The controversy of having a religious minister’s daughter claim to be in a Christian rock band; while living a much different life had caused her father’s ministry much embarrassment. The combination of this and the size of her father’s ministry caused him to appear on a late night talk show. This was quite a surprise when I was watching television one night.